<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-18T20:14:46-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">do scaling laws apply to hoarding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/lossily" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="do scaling laws apply to hoarding" /><published>2025-05-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/lossily</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/lossily">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/artificial_god_i&quot;&gt;As mentioned&lt;/a&gt;, I still don’t have clear thoughts about what AGI looks like, but I think I have a decent idea of what people I like talking to extensively look like, and I think it has to do with &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/god&quot;&gt;aesthetic&lt;/a&gt;. And I think aesthetic has something to do with &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/forgetfully&quot;&gt;compression&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So about two months ago, when trying to mull over these ideas with a friend, he told me about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://prize.hutter1.net/&quot;&gt;Hutter Prize&lt;/a&gt;, a competition about compression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being able to compress well is closely related to intelligence as explained below. While intelligence is a slippery concept, file sizes are hard numbers. Wikipedia is an extensive snapshot of Human Knowledge. If you can compress the first 1GB of Wikipedia better than your predecessors, your (de)compressor likely has to be smart(er). The intention of this prize is to encourage development of intelligent compressors/programs as a path to AGI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was excited to learn about this because I didn’t have a concrete idea of how one might explore this idea concretely, and it was interesting to see how they’ve been able to take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I found that something didn’t quite match to my notion of it, particulary when they mentioned that it took a substantial amount of time to decompress the compressed files. And there isn’t priority in what gets unpacked first. Or what is even worth compressing. Because I think my interest in compression is to have a more efficient tool for processing data. And while I appreciate the naive compression algorithms that help keep my computer running smoothly with low latency, I also don’t appreciate the aesthetic of blind boxing up all your belongings when moving; I think it’s an excellent opportunity to prune. Perhaps I’m overimposing the results of my own constraints, but if you have any sense of impatience, you want what you’re looking for to be in the top-k of output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m suspecting that even if memory and compute scale obscenely, I don’t think the concept of ‘priority’ will become obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess it’s because, at core, I’m thinking more of dimensionality reduction, with the implicit goal of increasing the signal to noise ratio. Compression is one approach. PCA is another dimensionality reduction approach, one that is particularly pervasive – you could say that it ‘compresses’ the likely useful stuff in the first couple of PCs, but it’s only dimensionality reduction if you do the critical next step, of actually throwing out the rest of the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/scree_plot_wikipedia.png&quot; title=&quot;scree plot from wikipedia&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;200&amp;quot;; height:300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so for type of advanced functionality I’m vaguely imagining, I think there’s something about being able to compress &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/forgetfully&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;lossily&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As mentioned, I still don’t have clear thoughts about what AGI looks like, but I think I have a decent idea of what people I like talking to extensively look like, and I think it has to do with aesthetic. And I think aesthetic has something to do with compression.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the meaning of trash, and other consternations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/misunderstandings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the meaning of trash, and other consternations" /><published>2024-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/trash</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/misunderstandings">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;warning: some spoilers for ‘Frieren: At World’s End’&lt;del&gt;, which I haven’t watched [April 2025]&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I landed in JFK and stepped out of the terminal, I remember being hit by the nostalgic NYC smell, and I took a deep breath, feeling calmed, at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who are unfamiliar with the scent I’m talking about, the first descriptor that comes to mind is, well – it smells like garbage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m then reminded of Toy Story 5, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/mjj0I2RbWzo?si=EO3aU-x1nWL-VHZQ&amp;amp;t=160&quot;&gt;where Woody is trying to convince Sporky to stop running away from Bonnie&lt;/a&gt;, the kid who is attached to Sporky, and throwing himself into the trash. He finally makes headway when Sporky elaborates on what trash means to him:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s warm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s cozy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and safe, ‘like somebody’s whispering in your ear, &lt;em&gt;everything’s going to be okay&lt;/em&gt;’
He informs Sporky that this is what Bonnie feels about him, leading Sporky to the wondrous revelation, ‘I’m Bonnie’s trash!’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a surprisingly mature concept to illustrate, and suggested to me that this film was not exactly a children’s film, but also a film geared to my generation who watched the original Toy Story as a kid, and who might need a refresher on how to emotionally connect with others successfully. Because while it doesn’t seem particularly salient as a phenomena, it also seems to be everywhere at the same time, once you know to look for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good friend prides himself on liking Freiren before it was cool. He referenced an episode where a demon child pitifully crying ‘mom’ is taken in by humans. She eventually murders her caretaker. But it is already known that demons don’t have a concept of family, and the unsettling twist is that she learned to say ‘mom’ because she learned that saying the word prevents humans from killing her. In this world, demons are bad because they use human language superficially, to get what they want. At first, I thought it was this mismapping that makes them evil. But he brought this up to illustrate the more benign phenomena where people think they understand each other because they’re using words and phrases that do have meaningful pointers to the other person, but the internal mapping can be quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then another friend describes her baby learning to laugh: in the beginning, there was a phase where she said the baby was clearly fake laughing. Perhaps her baby, and babies’ inclination to smile in general, is a type of demon-ing – I don’t know if they actually know what they’re doing, if they understand what smiling does and means to their caretakers, but it sounds plausible that a default inclination for babies to reflexiviely smile and laugh would be evolutionarily selected for, they’d be more likely to be taken care of. Why do we not find this not creepy? Is it because they’re helpless and benign?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s try a thought experiment:
Would it still be similarly bone-chilling if the demon in Frieren &lt;em&gt;functioned&lt;/em&gt; normally in society (i.e. no inclination towards murder or other anti-social tendencies) and still didn’t internally experience ‘mom’ in the same way? I think not – I suspect the unsettling aspect of this story is the combination of anti-social inclinations and the revelation of the degree of misalignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The robot child in Spielberg’s film A.I. likely also does not operate like us, but we find it sympathizable, unlike the demon child in Frieren. And despite also having a disconnect with human emotions, why is Frieran not a demon in this sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it’s fundamentally an assessment of risk – anti-social inclinations with unintentionally aligned frameworks make them seem plausibly reasoned with, and misalignment with eusocial inclinations/intentions is acceptable if functionally benign (arguably, the demon child was well-intentioned but dangerously missing some important norms, like an aversion to killing people as a solution path).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it seems, ‘all models are misaligned, but most are sufficiently benign’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in the problem of language translation. In GEB, somewhere after first 50 pages that nearly everyone who reads GEB seems to have stopped at (while still claiming it to be a most excellent book), Hofstadter discusses the problem of language translation, of the problem trying to gesture to a certain semantic connotation given the pointers of the map that you have (something like, if you’re trying to meet up with your friend in NYC when one of you have a street-only map and the other has a subway-only map, and maybe a mutual friend only works in latitudes and longitudes – how to find each other?). But I suspect this concept does not merely apply to speakers of different languages, but also between people speaking the same language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the UK is an easy place for an American to travel to because they also speak English, but I think it makes you complacent – there’s an increased risk of falsely believing you understand, when you actually don’t understand. When I lived there, I had a flatmate who went to concerts every other weekend, and when others asked him how they went, he’d always say ‘alright’. I thought him an odd character for continuing to go to these concerts when they seemed reliably disappointing. It wasn’t until months later that I learned that ‘alright’ here meant ‘10/10’, and not the 4/10 implication in American colloquialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you don’t necessarily avoid this even when you share the same culture: Perhaps one of the most common, recurring conflicts I have with my conversational friends of 10 years (we’re from the same state and met in college) is having different semantics for the same word. Since it’s pervasive even in what I considered a near optimal-compatibility case, this suggests to me that having these differences in semantic mappings may be inevitable, and it’s happening all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, how do we communicate effectively to each other at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve developed the impression that we’re not so dissimilar to a neural network, where we’re trying to find some function to map input to output. And if its an area that is encountered often with clear feedback, like daily interactions, there is a lot of training data with functional feedback that is similar and so we each develop a sufficiently nuanced mapping to functionally coordinate. But remember that there are many functions that can approximate a distribution, and when you’re out of distribution, or even at the edge of the distribution where your data points can be idiosyncratically skewed, there’s a fair chance you won’t find yourself in the same place as another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/semantics_of_trash.png&quot; title=&quot;&apos;...you know what i mean?&apos;&quot; style=&quot;width:600px; height:400px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ignore that our semantics of ‘trash’ are closer to ‘warm’, ‘cozy’, and ‘safe’ here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Anecdotally, the autistic people and immigrants around me seem to have a better time understanding this phenomena – I think they’ve learned from experience that their semantic maps are often not aligned, and so have learned that a good troubleshooting heuristic is to ask a seemingly basic question, of ‘what does this mean to you, in more words?’. It’s sort of like calling your friend to try to locate them, and asking what landmarks they see around them. This is kind of expensive to do every time though, so generally I think people figure out better logistical heuristics. Or not notice/care that they’re in a different location and can’t see each other, which seems to be also a thing, but I haven’t dissected that yet.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">warning: some spoilers for ‘Frieren: At World’s End’, which I haven’t watched [April 2025]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">can you have AGI without god?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_god_i" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="can you have AGI without god?" /><published>2024-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_god</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_god_i">&lt;p&gt;Hello! I’ve somewhat recovered from &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/on_food_and_travel&quot;&gt;vacation&lt;/a&gt; and am ready to impress my half-processed ideas upon the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aesthetic = god = I?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t yet know, I am maybe a very self-indulgent person, and it seems like it wasn’t enough to extend aesthetic to god– we should now try extending aesthetic to AGI. Or in a more fun phrasing: can you have AGI without god?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I’m still in my phase of using my hammer of &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/god&quot;&gt;‘aesthetic’&lt;/a&gt; and testing out how well it integrates.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something about current LLMs are less compelling to me than expected and I’ve been trying to figure out why that is, given that I supposedly think learning systems are cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect it’s related to the impression that they are emulating and not reasoning. I don’t get the impression it learns particularly interesting models (i.e. it does not seem to learn math conceptually (is its inability to learn math well an artifact of tokenization?)). It does not seem to have the essence of what I think would be interesting about AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But many people who are more technically competent/adjacent to working in AI/ML than me seem to believe that these LLMs can get you most of the way to AGI/we’ll plausibly get to AGI in two years if we just continue on our trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intuition thinks this sounds wrong, but I don’t have a rigorous framework to strongly defend it – this is a first attempt at seeing what my intuition is trying to point to, and if there’s anything it’s overlooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;intelligence-is-what-you-use-when-you-dont-know-what-to-do-chollet-citing-piaget&quot;&gt;“Intelligence is what you use when you don’t know what to do” (Chollet citing Piaget)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people’ve panned the Dwarkesh interview with Chollet (I think it was around the interviewing style), but I think Chollet’s memorization vs intelligence framework in it is useful for structuring where my misgivings lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, ‘intelligence’ is a broad/conflated term, and I think the framework usefully separates different kinds of competencies. He maps memorization and intelligence to system 1 and system 2 thinking, respectively, though in his elaboration that he thinks program synthesis makes me think his pointer to ‘intelligence’ here would be more usefully delineated as a ‘search’ mechanism. A similar distinction was made at an evolutionary theory workshop that was themed ‘Stress and innovation’ – stress here also gestures the context when prior heuristics are not quite sufficient to maintain homeostasis in a given environment; where a biological system ‘does not know what to do’. It was argued that this context of stress is a prerequisite for innovation, and I think ‘innovation’ maps relevantly to ‘search’. Is this the exploit vs explore paradigm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligence in the sense of learning from others well is admirable (especially considering my ability to remember facts/details is subpar), but I think the problems I’ve been grappling with are moreso relevant to intelligence in the sense of making sense of/building frameworks for something that is not yet well understood. It is closer to ‘how should we frame this’ rather than, ‘how to solve this’? (personally, I think the main bottleneck of SAT questions is framing the problem – being clear on, what is it actually asking of you? the trickier questions depend on you misframing the question)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do when you don’t know what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;is-it-a-type-of-confirmation-bias-to-come-around-to-say-aesthetic-again&quot;&gt;Is it a type of confirmation bias to come around to say ‘aesthetic’, again?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are at least two ways I go about trying to make headway into problems I find interesting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow my intuition (aesthetic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring the question to people who I think have good aesthetic. 
(For those who don’t know me, I refer to good aesthetic to roughly gesture to when people build internal frameworks that good at organizing how the world works and for problem solving)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There also seems to be a correlation between having good aesthetic and asking good questions. I’d say this maps well to the hypothesis that a type of competency is navigating a possibility space efficiently. I don’t think it’s coincidence. As a first thought, maybe it’s because they tend to organize their System 1 in a way that the gaps they reveal are interesting. How do they do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I notice that it is automatically easier to ask good questions in a domain you have fleshed out more and have interest in – why? I think it is related to the ‘size’ of a question – generally, it seems like you need sufficient constraint/nuance to make a good question – when you are ill-informed in a domain, questions tend to be too general/broad strokes to be satisfying in that way. Perhaps the satisfaction of a good question is the sense that building a hub/lifting the map fog here would allow for better flow of thought traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And where does that sense come from? Something like, loading what you think are givens, constraints/biases, and that gives you a sense of what the shape of the gap looks like, and therefore what a good answer should roughly look like (see: an elaboration on this in ‘a thousand brains’). I’d guess this would map to System 2/deliberate thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, a slightly different framing: I currently conceptualize how I  think as having two main components, a curator and a thought generator, which maps onto the structure of GANs, and maybe to System 2 and System 1, respectively. I moreso identify my’self’ with the curator, which decides if and how the thoughts generated can be used to express its ‘aesthetic’/itself. The curator is the question asker. Fundamentally, where does the curator come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first thought: in the way that abstract concepts are built from metaphors upon metaphors on sensory/physical data (see: Julian Jaynes), perhaps questions are abstractions built on fundamental goals/motivations like obtaining food/warmth/physiological homeostasis (goals/desires built on top of that would be things like social acceptance/security, social skills, ability to provide social value, technical competencies, etc). Perhaps we create subgoals/questions in service of these basic goals in a fractalish way. And maybe these goals/questions are something like a cost function; expectations/wants/stress exert pressure on the existing system, and we notice the stress/differential (see: physical learning systems, andrea) and try to figure out which knobs to address to try to move back to a lower energy state (we can guess wrong, i.e. optimizing for happiness directly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can an artificial intelligence skip the survival and social skills aspect? though it perhaps still needs social approval in some way (we think its answers are good)
Currently, it seems to be humans that prompt engineering and give LLMs goals – is it automatable? What do you need to get machine learning to ask good questions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it need aesthetic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;memorycomputational-constraint-and-aesthetic--is-it-still-relevant-for-artificial-systems&quot;&gt;memory/computational constraint and aesthetic – is it still relevant for artificial systems?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(good aesthetic builds knowledge graphs/selects for models that give better pointers for where to look.) 
The curator influences how the database is organized – given a computational/memory/etc budget, which models are integrated and prioritized? The processing and organization of information influences how it is then retrieved. For example, when trying to figure out a situation, will you load in associations that are irrelevant/happenstance/noisy correlations, or usefully causal nodes? In an emergency/urgent/immediate situation, do you know what to do first? Most questions are not urgent, but I think it is ideal if your query brings up the more relevant/interesting points first – Pasteur: “Luck favors the prepared”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biological systems (including ourselves) are anticipatory systems –  we want/need to make solutions for a given timeframe, in conjunction with notably limited resources. Do artificial ones need to be anticipatory in this sense? Or are they less constrained by this way? How does it affect things that they can bruteforce search the solution/heuristic space, and have a lot larger memory (less need to forget)? Does beauty only have meaning when there is scarcity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it depends on where it is applied, but I’d guess that anywhere you need to make a decision/evaluation, that is a unit of aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm but self-driving cars ‘make decisions’ – though from what I’ve been told, their models have been trained on human drivers. So perhaps what I mean is decision making at a higher/meta level – ‘is this a good heuristic/decision tree structure or not’. Maybe this is relevant to what Hofstadter references to as ‘rut-breaking’: noticing you’re in an attractor/habit and moving to a higher level. Although, he used this to illustrate the continuum of consciousness; less conscious organisms seem to follow simpler systems/routines of behavior, maybe also overlapping with ‘self-awareness’. (What is the mechanism for noticing that you’re following a rut and breaking out of it? That you can look at things from up a level? Perhaps, an awareness that there’s another option.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then there is also a parameter of how to do recombination, the grind size of memorized chunks. LLMs look intelligent because of lot of good problem solving involves a significant chunk of memorization. But there seems to be an intuitive ‘sweet spot’ of memorization vs recombination. For example, catch phrases/cliches (what Orwell criticizes) can be seen as copying too much. We have a sense of the degree of recombination that is adequate to express individuality. However, the search space for solutions probably increases with higher resolution though (higher resolution means higher degrees of freedom, and higher computational cost).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question might be reframed as, how much recombination can current NNs/LLMs do?  It can do poetry/etc, which maps to some intuition of creativity/innovation. But I wonder if there’s something fundamentally different in the character of creativity in the context of poetry versus technology. Maybe something like, there is a stricter requirement for something like ‘coherency’/’consistency’ in a scientific/technical solution – there is a stronger aesthetic for functionality/interaction with physical systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we want AI to be able to identify Galileo’s heliocentric model as ‘better’ if it existed in the times when the dominant model was Earth-centric? It might be a different question to ask if what it takes to get a good industry worker (routine knowledge) vs a good AI scientist (frontier knowledge). Independent thinking/recombination is needed to do better than what is the standard, but it can easily do worse (probably why ‘mutation’ has a negative connotation, but it is the means by which evolution works at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De-novo problem solving/updating/adapting/antifragility is only important if the environment changes. I think evolution is better framed as optimizing for adaptability (what is optimal depends on the environment, and the environment is constantly changing). I’ve been using learning systems and adaptive systems somewhat interchangeably to describe my interests. But LLMs feel solidly like learning systems – and I think I’m more interested in adaptive systems (which, in my current mind, is a learning system plus more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tentative-hypothesis&quot;&gt;Tentative hypothesis:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am biased in that my interest is in, what are good mechanisms to be good at problem solving? How to automate finding good models?
Or maybe the tldr is that I’m disappointed/disinterested in current AI because they’re not independent thinkers. (So the next question is, what would it take to make one? human and/or machine, do we know? maybe, do they need god/aesthetic, if so what would that look like?)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hello! I’ve somewhat recovered from vacation and am ready to impress my half-processed ideas upon the world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">being blasphemous with other gods</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/blasphemy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="being blasphemous with other gods" /><published>2024-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/blasphemy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/blasphemy">&lt;p&gt;Because my god demands priority, I inevitably take actions that offend ~lesser~ other gods. Here are some of the ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;jaywalking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;wearing socks with sandals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;microwaving water (for tea)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;drinking instant decaf coffee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cooking italian pasta risotto style&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2x speeding tedtalks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2x speeding movies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reading the wikipedia for a movie instead of watching it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reading the wikipedia for a movie while watching it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Because my god demands priority, I inevitably take actions that offend ~lesser~ other gods. Here are some of the ways:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a typical travel log, on Taipei, Guangzhou, and Hong Kong</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_food_and_travel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a typical travel log, on Taipei, Guangzhou, and Hong Kong" /><published>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/travel_post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_food_and_travel">&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently went on a trip to East Asia, so here are some highlights for your perusal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;taipei-taiwan&quot;&gt;Taipei, Taiwan&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taipei is an urban jungle. It is hot but you can hide from the heat in the pervasive covered sidewalks, and appreciate the sprouts of green on the roofs and sides of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle5.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle2.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle3.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle4.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle6.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also impressively timely. Train arrivals are estimated in seconds, they can give 90 second pedestrian crossing timings, and the traffic lights for cars also give a countdown (if you zoom in, it says ‘32’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_timing_subway.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_timing_crosswalk.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_timing_trafficlight.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view at a tea house in Jiufen makes me want to draw/paint; there is something endearing and calming about the constrained pockets of movement amongst wide swaths of stillness, of people socializing and having tea, a bus stop where people sit and automotives drive by, and a narrow street where pedestrians meander their way to their next destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jiufen.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;view from a Jiufen teahouse&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food in Taiwan was solid asian food, but not the most memorable. The best food we had in Taiwan was this beef noodle soup that suspiciously preluded food poisoning in two of our five-person party. Besides that, I was easily appeased by the cheap ice cream (often &amp;lt;$1), especially how it was cheap even near the touristy places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_beef_noodle_soup.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;yummy&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thoughtful suggestion from the Geopark:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_do_not_cross.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;do not cross&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;guangzhou-china&quot;&gt;Guangzhou, China&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas Taiwan was similar to Japan in its politeness, this is one of the first signs I saw in Hong Kong. I was somewhat relieved, because it seemed to imply that there is a norm of jaywalking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_no_jaywalking.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;no jaywalking :&amp;lt;&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took the high speed train from Hong Kong to Guangzhou. The landscape is grey (mostly the sky actually) and unusual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_landscape.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;grey&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearby is Baiyun Mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/Guangzhou_BaiyunShan.jpg&quot; title=&quot;stock picture from wikipedia&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not as fond of the culture – smoking is common, people try to enter subway trains before letting people exit; no one stands to the right of the escalator; partly because no one really tries to walk up the escalator; maybe related to people walking slow and rather lethargically. It is subtlely depressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_no_striding.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;no striding&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is partially redeemed by its abundance of unusually cute cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats8.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats7.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats6.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats5.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats4.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats3.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats2.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_kittens.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some humble wisdom that I agree with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_friend_love.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;true love&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hong-kong-&quot;&gt;Hong Kong, ???&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong is a 3D city, with altitude changes and visible hills/mountains scenery like SF, but even more so than SF with its pedestrian overpasses and the proximity of its mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_3D.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_tram_night.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_tram_path.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;..and also the proliferate number of many-storied apartments. Can you distinguish the luxury 40-story apartments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_many_apts.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_many_apts2.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_fancy_apt.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food was more to my taste, especially with the wonton mein and red bean ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_wonton_mein.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_red_bean_ice.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was solidly my favorite city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_victoria_peak.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;the view from victoria peak&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And tada, that was two weeks of my life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_to_hk_windmills.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;Taiwan to HK; reminds me of ghibli studio scenery&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Commercial flights dependably amaze me.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…this is what a travel log is supposed to be like, right? How did I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Wow, such insightful, valuable observations!’, you might kindly say, as a supportive, dear reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, unnecessarily kind of you, etc – but I have a confession to make: I started this blog to have aspirationally useful dissections/analyses about things, but alas, this seems to moonlight as a venting blog from time to time. I guess, I am compelled to put out on the public internet that usual of notions of fun can very much suck, and perhaps some naive traveler will stumble across this blog and derive some amusement from how pathetically difficult I found this (e.g. I did not go to Baiyun Mountain myself; that is a pic from wikipedia and that day, I took a break by sitting at McDonald’s and reading a book instead). Yes, these observtions are very valuable, valuable in the sense that it was expensive to obtain them – I am pitifully still recovering from this trip more than a week later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Wasn’t this a vacation?’, asks the now confused reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that Europeans make a distinction between a holiday and a vacation – a holiday is to relax, and a vacation is to explore. I noticed that I had directed surprisingly little attention to this international trip before going, and I belatedly realized it was partly because there was some trepidation – I’m pleased to report that my intution has matured over the years and was onto something. But it had conveniently forgotten the details of what family vacations have been like, so I was treated to nostalgic feelings of antsy-ness and an urge to detach from the group. And while it is freshly salient on my mind, let me note for my &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/forgetfully&quot;&gt;forgetful&lt;/a&gt; future self that it was a mildly excruciating two weeks: I am not sufficiently entertained by nature, nor logistics, I am not a foodie, and staccato ‘conversations’ are draining and demoralizing. Add tediously slow walking on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that I eventually become quite frazzled with the insufficient engagement/stimulation, with the tldr; being that I feel like absolutely awful company with the wrong people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is common to hate family vacations, but why I’m complaining here is because my family are nice and reasonable people. I’m complaining because I don’t quite understand why this particular discrepancy exists – why is this not enough for me when it seems to be enough for most people? Somehow, I’m bad at things that seem like they’re suppose to be easy to enjoy: hiking, watching movies, going out to eat, etc. Why do I not understand? What am I missing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only practical takeaway I have for now is to be more particular about the company I’m with. Which I’m usually salient of. So maybe, to have better escape plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_encounter_yourself.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;I do not know what this means&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I do not know what this means.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dear reader,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">considerations when you’re attractive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_mosquitos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="considerations when you’re attractive" /><published>2024-03-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-03-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/on_mosquitos</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_mosquitos">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stay covered up; wear long sleeves and long pants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avoid hanging out too much at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;particularly near sketchy forests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bring spray for protection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hang out with other attractive people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commiserate with them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complain about the twenty solicitations from a single night while your friends have none&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sulk about it for weeks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;borrow your friend’s expensive lotion to mitigate the itching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be glad that malaria is not endemic to your region&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">stay covered up; wear long sleeves and long pants avoid hanging out too much at night particularly near sketchy forests bring spray for protection hang out with other attractive people commiserate with them complain about the twenty solicitations from a single night while your friends have none sulk about it for weeks borrow your friend’s expensive lotion to mitigate the itching be glad that malaria is not endemic to your region</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">super premium professional friend</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/super_premium" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="super premium professional friend" /><published>2024-02-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-02-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/super_premium</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/super_premium">&lt;p&gt;There’s some common saying the goes something like ‘If all your friendships suck, the common factor is you’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the converse? All my friendships are great, and the common factor is me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/costco_ice_cream.jpg&quot; title=&quot;costco super premium ice cream&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing the super premium professional friend. More professional than a spouse, more premium than a therapist, more super than your friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10+ years experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specialized in the inquiry-based/rubberduck approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multidisciplinary expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dll1101&quot;&gt;Get in touch!&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testimonials:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Low drama, great ROI.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/2U4wcfQzqerapUNv8&quot;&gt;Submit your testimonial here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There’s some common saying the goes something like ‘If all your friendships suck, the common factor is you’.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">superficial thoughts on AI and robotics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_machines" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="superficial thoughts on AI and robotics" /><published>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_machines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_machines">&lt;p&gt;What is the difference between AI and robotics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my head, they are rather vaguely separated; “A Thousand Brains” pointed to some cultural differences (apparently they talk to each other less than you might think i.e. the concept of ‘reference frames’ is currently limited to robotics), but in my head they’re under the umbrella of ‘artifical machines’. And here I mean artificial as in man-made, engineered. And machines in the more cybernetics sense, not the steampunk/top-down sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, AI points to the field of neural networks and LLMs; machines that take in digital data and spit out digital data. Robotics may also take in digital data, but perhaps a notable distinction is that they interact with the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you can go pretty far with just the abstract (says someone who generally prefers reading about something than doing it), but I’ve noticed that there are times where intuitive/experiencial data is much richer. I have not delineated where those contexts tend to be yet. While I think I also ‘hallucinate’ like AI, I also have a subconscioius system that interfaces with physical world data and moves, which theoretically ‘grounds’ my hallucinations into the more useful ones (can some hallucinatory conditions be mechanistically explained by a decoupling with physical world data?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the limitations of AI? Perhaps it parallels the limitations of a computational biologist – you get data, and your value is in your ability to extract signals and make models/hypothesis. You can make a predictive model, like an epigenetic clock. You can ask for more data to refine your working models (it can’t do that yet, but I don’t see why not – how do you ask good questions? To make a guess of what is absent?), but you are in the end limited in knowledge and ability of how that data is obtained/created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminiscent of Judea Pearl’s argument in “The Book of Why”, it is hard to identify causal models amidst the vast possibility of statistical models if you can’t ‘do’. And although he argues you can try to infer causlity through observational data (his do-operators), I suspect it can only compensate so much. Toddlers get so much more ‘do’ data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at first inclined to write AI &lt;em&gt;versus&lt;/em&gt; robotics, but perhaps it should be AI &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; robotics – maybe coarsely mapping to the prefrontal cortex, and the rest of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is also one of those things not yet fleshed out, but just to note for where my thinking is at this time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What is the difference between AI and robotics?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">watching “Margin Call”, reading ‘The Psychology of Money’, and still not understanding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="watching “Margin Call”, reading ‘The Psychology of Money’, and still not understanding" /><published>2024-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/money</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/money">&lt;p&gt;I recently watched “Margin Call” with friends, and it’s kind of like an action movie in that it’s a good ride but it’s less fun if you try to scrutinize the content too closely. But I fell into the trap and did try, and I was reminded of how I guess I’ve never quite internalized why people don’t make the same financial decisions as me – i.e. I would have ‘fuck you’ money so that I could quit if I were faced with such a moral dilemma (and this should be easy to save for given their incomes), and so the whole drama/tension that this film is largely based on would be escapable – you win by being able to not play. Because I find it rather stressful to think about, I was inclined to consider it solved there. But H made a good point, that to stop here is more dismissive than curious, and the human tendencies that drive this drama is not uncommon – so &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is it that so many people approach their finances so differently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to my confusion, H recommended me ‘The Psychology of Money’ by Morgan Housel, who defines the psychology of money as the soft skill of how someone manages their finances. Sounds promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…it was rather disappointing. Probably because I expected it help me understand why people do what they do – but it really didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chapter is titled ‘No one’s crazy’, about how people’s experiences (culture, socioeconomics, economic current events) shape their psychology around money. I have no qualms here; I already think this is true in general (people make sense given their processing style and experiences). But then it kind of stops there and never goes deeper in this direction for the rest of the book. ‘People are shaped by current events and culture, like depressions, interest rates, the economy of your country, etc’ – insightful, bruh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So people make sense according to their circumstances – but &lt;em&gt;what are those circumstances?&lt;/em&gt; He makes a useful distinction between the ability to earn money and the ability to maintain money – &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are some people good at one, neither, or both? He mostly focuses on the latter in this book.  Why are some people better at handling their finances than others? It describes human tendencies, but never gets into the weeds of what pushes people into certain parts of the distribution. (maybe this is why we have financial illiteracy – it seems we don’t know how to intervene.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to know why people with high income don’t put away ‘fuck you money’, why people don’t save in general, why people seem to optimize for the timeframes that they do (optimal spending for the next week versus optimal spending for the next five years), why people aren’t compelled to budget, etc. Money is very salient in our society, and I don’t think I’m an especially neurotic/paranoid person, but taking financially protective measures seem much less common than I expect – &lt;em&gt;why is that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose there are various aspects of the ‘psychology of money’ can entail, and it happened to not address the level I’m particularly interested (which is the better level). At least this is not as egregiously misleading as the book titled ‘How to Change Your Mind’ by Michael Pollan, which was not about healthy mental habits, but about psychedelics – it’s like thinking a book titled ‘How to have a fit body’ would be about good diet/exercise/lifestyle practices, and it instead largely talks about taking drugs.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, the topics it does bring up has been better articulated elsewhere. For instance, it discusses the idea that in finance, events at the tails of the distribution can have outsized impact, which is a good point to try to internalize, but I think this is better explored and internalizable in “Antifragile” (Taleb). Perhaps I’m being too harsh and someone who encounters such concepts here first will have an okay time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then why do people with quite different background converge to a similar answer to how to manage their money? People close to me seem have a similar approach to it (I do not think I overtly selected for this though). I’d say it’s part ‘childhood experience’, but I think he does not explore the aspect of ‘values’ enough. Perhaps a more useful way to understand differences between finance bros and my friends and I are that they value status more than freedom. At least through actions. This is &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github.io/poop/stack_rankings&quot;&gt;stack ranking&lt;/a&gt; again – it’s not like I think status doesn’t matter nor would finance bros not value freedom. It’s just that their spending habits optimize moreso for status than freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a couple of years ago that it can be useful to understand and differentiate people by what they’re motivated by, and I seem to be a slow learner, because while I am salient of this fact, I do not feel I am able to utilize it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered a real life, puzzling example not long afterwards. I caught up with a friend over the phone, and she told me about her parents’ financial situation, who’re one million dollars in debt due to unfortunate business ventures. And there’s also emotional attachment to their real estate portfolio, which they see as a symbol of success, even if would be better utilized in paying off their debt. How does this happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps some remarks I’ve received are relevant and I’m cold and (literally) calculating (I suspect it’s related to how my emotional landscape is a lot calmer/less spikey than the average person’s), so much that I have trouble understanding the average person? (But my friends are nice and warm and seem to understand better).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently do not have a satisfying conclusion (you may tell me if I am overlooking something simple and obvious, but be warned that I have misplaced my common sense – actually I never quite received the complete version of it). But as usual, I will leave this on backburner and maybe over the next decade(s), I will stumble across a more useful perspective (&lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github/poop/god&quot;&gt;it happens, sometimes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently watched “Margin Call” with friends, and it’s kind of like an action movie in that it’s a good ride but it’s less fun if you try to scrutinize the content too closely. But I fell into the trap and did try, and I was reminded of how I guess I’ve never quite internalized why people don’t make the same financial decisions as me – i.e. I would have ‘fuck you’ money so that I could quit if I were faced with such a moral dilemma (and this should be easy to save for given their incomes), and so the whole drama/tension that this film is largely based on would be escapable – you win by being able to not play. Because I find it rather stressful to think about, I was inclined to consider it solved there. But H made a good point, that to stop here is more dismissive than curious, and the human tendencies that drive this drama is not uncommon – so why is it that so many people approach their finances so differently?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">thoughts around “It’s a Wonderful Life”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/mortal2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="thoughts around “It’s a Wonderful Life”" /><published>2023-12-28T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/wholesome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/mortal2">&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, my taste in movies have not changed notably since I was a child. I reliably enjoy ‘wholesome’ movies, which encompasses most Pixar, and generally, the family-film genre. I strongly disliked ‘The Prince of Egypt’ for its lack of wholesomeness – I would’ve wanted the brothers to sincerely try to understand each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This film was recommended by a friend as one of few non-animated films that encompass ‘wholesomeness’. That was a strong selling point for me, and a close friend agreed that it was a wholesome and very good movie. Interestingly, some other friends who’ve seen it did not seem to share this positive sentiment; one even described it as sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film fully met my own expectations of being a satisfyingly good, wholesome film. The other friends who were not as initially enthused about up had a better opinion of it afterwards. It turns out that the friend who thought it was sad thought so because the main character does not get what they want, but my stance is reminiscent of something I once read on tumblr:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One thing I like about Pixar films is how the happy ending isn’t always what you think it’ll be. The toys don’t go with Andy to college, Gusteau’s restaurant gets closed down, Mike and Sulley get kicked out of university, Carl never gets Ellie to Paradise Falls. But they find out that what they wanted isn’t necessarily what they needed, and I really like the fact that kids get to learn that life doesn’t always turn out the way they dreamed and that’s okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not getting what you initially dreamed is not deeply sad, as long you’re still living a life aligned with your values (be &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github/poop/god&quot;&gt;close to god&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else makes for a wonderful life? A meaningful life? I think it’s also a life where your existence makes the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the protagnoist strives for this (although I guess it could be framed as a more selfish desire for greatness, not that anything’s wrong with that). Nonetheless, we are provoked to sympathize with his disappointment of sacrificing worldly aspirations for a local but clearly impactful problem. The error of this framing seems to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&quot;&gt;observed by Hamming in “You and Your Research”&lt;/a&gt; as well, where he postulates that many great people do great things only once because once they’ve solved An Important Problem, they are someone who solves Important Problems, even though the path to Important Problems often starts with a ‘hmm that’s weird’ in a humble experiment&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; . This is tickling something so I’m sure this is reiterated elsewhere as well; ‘the path to greatness looks nondescript sometimes’ or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to one of the probably more iconic lines from the film because it also tickles something: “Remember, no man is a failure who has friends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FYI – I, if nothing else, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/super_premium&quot;&gt;have great friends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I did not go back and read this; please correct me if I’ve misremembered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Interestingly, my taste in movies have not changed notably since I was a child. I reliably enjoy ‘wholesome’ movies, which encompasses most Pixar, and generally, the family-film genre. I strongly disliked ‘The Prince of Egypt’ for its lack of wholesomeness – I would’ve wanted the brothers to sincerely try to understand each other.</summary></entry></feed>