<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-14T20:07:58-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">a typical travel log, on Taipei, Guangzhou, and Hong Kong</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_food_and_travel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a typical travel log, on Taipei, Guangzhou, and Hong Kong" /><published>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/travel_post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_food_and_travel">&lt;p&gt;Dear reader,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently went on a trip to East Asia, so here are some highlights for your perusal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;taipei-taiwan&quot;&gt;Taipei, Taiwan&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taipei is an urban jungle. It is hot but you can hide from the heat in the pervasive covered sidewalks, and appreciate the sprouts of green on the roofs and sides of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle5.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle2.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle3.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle4.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jungle6.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also impressively timely. Train arrivals are estimated in seconds, they can give 90 second pedestrian crossing timings, and the traffic lights for cars also give a countdown (if you zoom in, it says ‘32’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_timing_subway.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_timing_crosswalk.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_timing_trafficlight.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view at a tea house in Jiufen makes me want to draw/paint; there is something endearing and calming about the constrained pockets of movement amongst wide swaths of stillness, of people socializing and having tea, a bus stop where people sit and automotives drive by, and a narrow street where pedestrians meander their way to their next destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_jiufen.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;view from a Jiufen teahouse&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food in Taiwan was solid asian food, but not the most memorable. The best food we had in Taiwan was this beef noodle soup that suspiciously preluded food poisoning in two of our five-person party. Besides that, I was easily appeased by the cheap ice cream (often &amp;lt;$1), especially how it was cheap even near the touristy places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_beef_noodle_soup.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;yummy&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A suggestion from the Geopark:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_do_not_cross.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;do not cross&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;guangzhou-china&quot;&gt;Guangzhou, China&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas Taiwan was similar to Japan in its politeness, this is one of the first signs I saw in Hong Kong. I was somewhat relieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_no_jaywalking.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;no jaywalking :&amp;lt;&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took the high speed train from Hong Kong to Guangzhou. The landscape is grey and unusual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_landscape.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;grey&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearby is Baiyun Mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/Guangzhou_BaiyunShan.jpg&quot; title=&quot;stock picture from wikipedia&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not as fond of the culture – smoking is common, people try to enter subway trains before letting people exit; no one stands to the right of the escalator; partly because no one really tries to walk up the escalator; maybe related to people walking slow and rather lethargically. It is subtlely depressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_no_striding.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;no striding&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is partially redeemed by its abundance of unusually cute cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats8.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats7.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats6.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats5.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats4.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats3.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_cats2.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_kittens.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some humble wisdom that I agree with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_friend_love.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;true love&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hong-kong-&quot;&gt;Hong Kong, ???&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong is a 3D city, with altitude changes and visible hills/mountains scenery like SF, but even more so than SF with its pedestrian overpasses and the proximity of its mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_3D.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_tram_night.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_tram_path.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;..and also the proliferate number of many-storied apartments. Can you distinguish the luxury 40-story apartments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_many_apts.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_many_apts2.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_fancy_apt.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;250&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food was more to my taste, especially with the wonton mein and red bean ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p float=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_wonton_mein.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_red_bean_ice.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was solidly my favorite city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/hk_victoria_peak.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;the view from victoria peak&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And tada, that was two weeks of my life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/tp_to_hk_windmills.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;Taiwan to HK; reminds me of ghibli studio scenery&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Commercial flights dependably amaze me.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…this is what a travel log is supposed to be like, right? How did I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Wow, such insightful, valuable observations!’, you might kindly say, as a supportive, dear reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, thank you – but I have a confession to make: I started this blog to have aspirationally useful dissections/analyses about things, but alas, this seems to moonlight as a venting blog from time to time. I guess, I am compelled to put out on the public internet that usual of notions of fun can very much suck, and perhaps some naive traveler will stumble across this blog and derive some amusement from how pathetically difficult I found this (e.g. I did not go to Baiyun Mountain myself; that is a pic from wikipedia and that day, I took a break by sitting at McDonald’s and reading a book instead). Yes, these observtions are very valuable, valuable in the sense that it was expensive to obtain them – I am pitifully still recovering from this trip more than a week later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Wasn’t this a vacation?’, asks the now confused reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that Europeans make a distinction between a holiday and a vacation – a holiday is to relax, and a vacation is to explore. I noticed that I had directed surprisingly little attention to this international trip before going, and I belatedly realized it was partly because there was some trepidation – I’m pleased to report that my intution has matured over the years and was onto something. But it had conveniently forgotten the details of what family vacations have been like, so I was treated to nostalgic feelings of antsy-ness and an urge to detach from the group. And while it is freshly salient on my mind, let me note for my forgetful future self that it was a mildly excruciating two weeks: I am not sufficiently entertained by nature, nor logistics, I am not a foodie, and staccotto ‘conversations’ are draining and demoralizing. Add slow walking on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that I eventually become quite frazzled with the insufficient engagement/stimulation, with the tldr; being that I’m absolutely horrible company with the wrong people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is common to hate family vacations, but why I’m complaining here is because my family are nice and reasonable people. I’m complaining because I don’t quite understand why this particular discrepancy exists – why is this not enough for me when it seems to be enough for most people? Somehow, I’m bad at things that seem like they’re suppose to be easy to enjoy: hiking, watching movies, going out to eat, etc. Why do I not understand? What am I missing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only practical takeaway I have for now is to be more particular about the company I’m with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/east_asia_2024/gz_encounter_yourself.jpeg&quot; title=&quot;I do not know what this means&quot; style=&quot;height:500px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I do not know what this means.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dear reader,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">considerations when you’re attractive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_mosquitos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="considerations when you’re attractive" /><published>2024-03-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-03-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/on_mosquitos</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/on_mosquitos">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stay covered up; wear long sleeves and long pants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avoid hanging out too much at night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;particularly near sketchy forests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bring spray for protection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hang out with other attractive people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commiserate with them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complain about the twenty solicitations from a single night while your friends have none&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sulk about it for weeks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;borrow your friend’s expensive lotion to mitigate the itching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be glad that malaria is not endemic to your region&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">stay covered up; wear long sleeves and long pants avoid hanging out too much at night particularly near sketchy forests bring spray for protection hang out with other attractive people commiserate with them complain about the twenty solicitations from a single night while your friends have none sulk about it for weeks borrow your friend’s expensive lotion to mitigate the itching be glad that malaria is not endemic to your region</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">superficial thoughts on AI and robotics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_machines" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="superficial thoughts on AI and robotics" /><published>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_machines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/artificial_machines">&lt;p&gt;What is the difference between AI and robotics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my head, they are rather vaguely separated; “A Thousand Brains” pointed to some cultural differences (apparently they talk to each other less than you might think i.e. the concept of ‘reference frames’ is currently limited to robotics), but in my head they’re under the umbrella of ‘artifical machines’. And here I mean artificial as in man-made, engineered. And machines in the more cybernetics sense, not the steampunk/top-down sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, AI points to the field of neural networks and LLMs; machines that take in digital data and spit out digital data. Robotics may also take in digital data, but perhaps a notable distinction is that they interact with the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you can go pretty far with just the abstract (says someone who generally prefers reading about something than doing it), but I’ve noticed that there are times where intuitive/experiencial data is much richer. I have not delineated where those contexts tend to be yet. While I think I also ‘hallucinate’ like AI, I also have a subconscioius system that interfaces with physical world data and moves, which theoretically ‘grounds’ my hallucinations into the more useful ones (can some hallucinatory conditions be mechanistically explained by a decoupling with physical world data?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are the limitations of AI? Perhaps it parallels the limitations of a computational biologist – you get data, and your value is in your ability to extract signals and make models/hypothesis. You can make a predictive model, like an epigenetic clock. You can ask for more data to refine your working models (it can’t do that yet, but I don’t see why not – how do you ask good questions? To make a guess of what is absent?), but you are in the end limited in knowledge and ability of how that data is obtained/created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminiscent of Judea Pearl’s argument in “The Book of Why”, it is hard to identify causal models amidst the vast possibility of statistical models if you can’t ‘do’. And although he argues you can try to infer causlity through observational data (his do-operators), I suspect it can only compensate so much. Toddlers get so much more ‘do’ data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at first inclined to write AI &lt;em&gt;versus&lt;/em&gt; robotics, but perhaps it should be AI &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; robotics – maybe coarsely mapping to the prefrontal cortex, and the rest of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is also one of those things not yet fleshed out, but just to note for where my thinking is at this time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What is the difference between AI and robotics?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">watching “Margin Call”, reading ‘The Psychology of Money’, and still not understanding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/money" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="watching “Margin Call”, reading ‘The Psychology of Money’, and still not understanding" /><published>2024-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/money</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/money">&lt;p&gt;I recently watched “Margin Call” with friends, and it’s kind of like an action movie in that it’s a good ride but it’s less fun if you try to scrutinize the content too closely. But I fell into the trap and did try, and I was reminded of how I guess I’ve never quite internalized why people don’t make the same financial decisions as me – i.e. I would have ‘fuck you’ money so that I could quit if I were faced with such a moral dilemma (and this should be easy to save for given their incomes), and so the whole drama/tension that this film is largely based on would be escapable – you win by being able to not play. Because I find it rather stressful to think about, I was inclined to consider it solved there. But H made a good point, that to stop here is more dismissive than curious, and the human tendencies that drive this drama is not uncommon – so &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is it that so many people approach their finances so differently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to my confusion, H recommended me ‘The Psychology of Money’ by Morgan Housel, who defines the psychology of money as the soft skill of how someone manages their finances. Sounds promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…it was rather disappointing. Probably because I expected it help me understand why people do what they do – but it really didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chapter is titled ‘No one’s crazy’, about how people’s experiences (culture, socioeconomics, economic current events) shape their psychology around money. I have no qualms here; I already think this is true in general (people make sense given their processing style and experiences). But then it kind of stops there and never goes deeper in this direction for the rest of the book. ‘People are shaped by current events and culture, like depressions, interest rates, the economy of your country, etc’ – insightful, bruh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So people make sense according to their circumstances – but &lt;em&gt;what are those circumstances?&lt;/em&gt; He makes a useful distinction between the ability to earn money and the ability to maintain money – &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; are some people good at one, neither, or both? He mostly focuses on the latter in this book.  Why are some people better at handling their finances than others? It describes human tendencies, but never gets into the weeds of what pushes people into certain parts of the distribution. (maybe this is why we have financial illiteracy – it seems we don’t know how to intervene.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to know why people with high income don’t put away ‘fuck you money’, why people don’t save in general, why people seem to optimize for the timeframes that they do (optimal spending for the next week versus optimal spending for the next five years), why people aren’t compelled to budget, etc. Money is very salient in our society, and I don’t think I’m an especially neurotic/paranoid person, but taking financially protective measures seem much less common than I expect – &lt;em&gt;why is that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose there are various aspects of the ‘psychology of money’ can entail, and it happened to not address the level I’m particularly interested (which is the better level). At least this is not as egregiously misleading as the book titled ‘How to Change Your Mind’ by Michael Pollan, which was not about healthy mental habits, but about psychedelics – it’s like thinking a book titled ‘How to have a fit body’ would be about good diet/exercise/lifestyle practices, and it instead largely talks about taking drugs.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, the topics it does bring up has been better articulated elsewhere. For instace, it discusses the idea that in finance, events at the tails of the distribution can have outsized impact, which is a good point to try to internalize, but I think this is better explored and internalizable in “Antifragile” (Taleb). Perhaps I’m being too harsh and someone who encounters such concepts here first will have an okay time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then why do people with quite different background converge to a similar answer to how to manage their money? People close to me seem have a similar approach to it (I do not think I overtly selected for this though). I’d say it’s part ‘childhood experience’, but I think he does not explore the aspect of ‘values’ enough. Perhaps a more useful way to understand differences between finance bros and my friends and I are that they value status more than freedom. At least through actions. This is stackranking again – it’s not like I think status doesn’t matter nor would finance bros not value freedom. It’s just that their spending habits optimize moreso for status than freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a couple of years ago that it can be useful to understand and differentiate people by what they’re motivated by, and I seem to be a slow learner, because while I am salient of this fact, I do not feel I am able to utilize it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered a real life, puzzling example not long afterwards. I caught up with a friend over the phone, and she told me about her parents’ financial situation, who’re one million dollars in debt due to unfortunate business ventures. And there’s also emotional attachment to their real estate portfolio, which they see as a symbol of success, even if would be better utilized in paying off their debt. How does this happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps some remarks I’ve received are relevant and I’m cold and (literally) calculating (I suspect it’s related to how my emotional landscape is a lot calmer/less spikey than the average person’s), so much that I have trouble understanding the average person? (But my friends are nice and warm and seem to understand better).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I currently do not have a satisfying conclusion (you may tell me if I am overlooking something simple and obvious, but be warned that I have misplaced my common sense). But as usual, I will leave this on backburner and maybe over the next decade(s), I will stumble across a more useful perspective (&lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github/poop/god&quot;&gt;it happens, sometimes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently watched “Margin Call” with friends, and it’s kind of like an action movie in that it’s a good ride but it’s less fun if you try to scrutinize the content too closely. But I fell into the trap and did try, and I was reminded of how I guess I’ve never quite internalized why people don’t make the same financial decisions as me – i.e. I would have ‘fuck you’ money so that I could quit if I were faced with such a moral dilemma (and this should be easy to save for given their incomes), and so the whole drama/tension that this film is largely based on would be escapable – you win by being able to not play. Because I find it rather stressful to think about, I was inclined to consider it solved there. But H made a good point, that to stop here is more dismissive than curious, and the human tendencies that drive this drama is not uncommon – so why is it that so many people approach their finances so differently?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">thoughts around “It’s a Wonderful Life”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/mortal2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="thoughts around “It’s a Wonderful Life”" /><published>2023-12-28T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/wholesome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/mortal2">&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, my taste in movies have not changed notably since I was a child. I reliably enjoy ‘wholesome’ movies, which encompasses most Pixar, and generally, the family-film genre. I strongly disliked ‘The Prince of Egypt’ for its lack of wholesomeness – I would’ve wanted the brothers to sincerely try to understand each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This film was recommended by a friend as one of few non-animated films that encompass ‘wholesomeness’. That was a strong selling point for me, and a close friend agreed that it was a wholesome and very good movie. Interestingly, some other friends who’ve seen it did not seem to share this positive sentiment; one even described it as sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film fully met my expectations of being a satisfyingly good, wholesome film. The other friends who were not as initially enthused about up had a better opinion of it afterwards. It turns out that the friend who thought it was sad thought so because the main character does not get what they want, but my stance is reminiscent of something I once read on tumblr:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One thing I like about Pixar films is how the happy ending isn’t always what you think it’ll be. The toys don’t go with Andy to college, Gusteau’s restaurant gets closed down, Mike and Sulley get kicked out of university, Carl never gets Ellie to Paradise Falls. But they find out that what they wanted isn’t necessarily what they needed, and I really like the fact that kids get to learn that life doesn’t always turn out the way they dreamed and that’s okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not getting what you initially dreamed is not deeply sad, as long you’re still living a life aligned with your values (be &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github/poop/god&quot;&gt;close to god&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else makes for a wonderful life? A meaningful life? I think it’s also a life where your existence makes the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the protagnoist strives for this (although I guess it could be framed as a more selfish desire for greatness, not that anything’s wrong with that). Nonetheless, we are provoked to sympathize with his disappointment of sacrificing worldly aspirations for a local but clearly impactful problem. The error of this framing seems to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&quot;&gt;observed by Hamming in “You and Your Research”&lt;/a&gt; as well, where he postulates that many great people do great things only once because once they’ve solved An Important Problem, they are someone who solves Important Problems, even though the path to Important Problems often starts with a ‘hmm that’s weird’ in a humble experiment^1^. This is tickling something so I’m sure this is reiterated elsewhere as well; ‘the path to greatness looks nondescript sometimes’ or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to one of the probably more iconic lines from the film because it also tickles something: “Remember, no man is a failure who has friends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FYI – I, if nothing else, &lt;a href=&quot;dll119/github.io/poop/professional_friend&quot;&gt;have great friends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I did not go back and read this; please correct me if I’ve misremembered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Interestingly, my taste in movies have not changed notably since I was a child. I reliably enjoy ‘wholesome’ movies, which encompasses most Pixar, and generally, the family-film genre. I strongly disliked ‘The Prince of Egypt’ for its lack of wholesomeness – I would’ve wanted the brothers to sincerely try to understand each other.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">some scattered, non-comprehensive reflections on aging and mortality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/mortal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="some scattered, non-comprehensive reflections on aging and mortality" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/mortality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/mortal">&lt;p&gt;[2023/12/21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last grandparent died yesterday morning, at the grand old age of 96. I last saw her in October, for her birthday banquet dinner. She still had a firm grip when I shook her hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dad had sent me her medical report the other day. I’m not a doctor (but I used to manually extract information from electronic medical records (EMRs) for clinical research) but most of her physiological systems looked serviceable. The main problem seemed to be her kidneys; she had end-stage renal disease (ESRD – reading clinical notes is largely in recognizing all the acronyms). And she was in the hospital because access point for dialysis had gotten infected, so they had used emergency access points, and were having trouble finding a permanent access point to be able to discharge her. Then, it seems like they had trouble removing excess fluid the day before she died, and she already had hypertension (HTN). It seems she died in her sleep this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chatted with my family after hearing the news; my mother mentions how 30 years ago, my grandmother came to stay with them to help out with Vic around my birth. My memories of her are clearest when they are from when I was less than 10 years old – she was much more active then. I remember playing at her sunny house with my sister; I was maybe 4. She might’ve had a garden at that point. I would ask her to wrap a doll up like you would a baby, and she’d oblige every time (the wrapping would come apart after some time). When I was elementary-school-aged, she obliged in scratching my back when I was watching a movie at my aunt’s house (I had chronic eczema) until my back was sore (I had asked her to). She made these ‘crystal skin’ dumplings filled with water chestnut, dried shrimp, mushrooms, which I’ve never seen elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not know her particularly well, but my mom loved her deeply, and her death feels like the end of an era, maybe in how childhood feels so much more nostalgic and bittersweet now – figures from that era will inevitably fall away (eventually it will be my own parents).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the passing thought the other day, that another upside to having quit my PhD is that I’m not as officially tied to the field of aging. It is perhaps notable how uninterested I am to it compared to the average person I encounter. And then I do not want them to find out that I used to work on it because &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github.io/poop/independently&quot;&gt;I feel like a party pooper every time&lt;/a&gt;, holding a pessimistic/apathetic attitude towards their hope against a deep-seated fear (AFAICT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it would be good for me to be wrong, but I can’t help but feel a bit of validation when my skepticism pans out. For example, I was surprised to hear that a longevity drug ‘passed’ FDA approval; I’m not surprised to now learn that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/vHSkxmYYqW59sySqA/the-likely-first-longevity-drug-is-based-on-sketchy-science&quot;&gt;it has low proof of efficacy&lt;/a&gt;. There was another tweet recently about how RetroBio wants to add 10 years to everyone. Perhaps I’m complacent because my grandparents have almost all made it to their 90s, and it’s not clear to me that they would’ve benefited greatly from same solution you’d try to give the average person to extend their life 10 years (death from cardiovascular disease or cancer, I’m guessing?). I am not sure how senolytics, say, will address or prevent ESRD. The mechanistic connection seems far, from the perspective over here. Generally, I think it’s theoretically possible, but I suspect it’s much more complicated than they make it seem (I’m reminded of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_on_cancer&quot;&gt;the ‘war on cancer’&lt;/a&gt;). And I guess it’s not really constructive criticism, but it does not quite seem like the right shape of a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not saliently consider that you could have a lightpost to mark your life (I saw a lamppost casted with a dedication on a walk recently), but if that’s possible, I’d much prefer that to a gravestone. (What about a lightpost that can hold a few books?) Even a bench would be cooler. (A joint lightpost, bench with a close friend/family would be greatly satisfying, with a little library in proximity). I should make some sketches at some point.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">[2023/12/21]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">some initial thoughts around mech interp</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/trying_mi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="some initial thoughts around mech interp" /><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/mechinterp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/trying_mi">&lt;p&gt;When I brought up the idea that i was considering a pivot into mech interp, my closest friends were baffled. It seemed like quite the nonsequitor, even flighty, said one friend. Which was surprising for me, because the connection seemed obvious, but then again, I tend to model the outside perspective poorly. Another of those friends had previously said that it took time to learn that my seemingly random tangents are usually not actually random, it’s just that I tend to explain the connection poorly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is a somewhat scattered attempt to explain the potential relations between my more established interests and mech interp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my most public interest is in the biomedical sciences, as that’s what’s most legible in my career path. But I suspect what I like in biology is highly specific, and it does not include being in nature or benchwork. I guess it leans more theoretical, which is why I like evolutionary biology. I like Rosen’s framing of it, with biology as ‘anticipatory systems’, or systems that anticipate their future environment and state, and try to best position themselves given that anticipation. In this framing, you can think of more intelligent systems as those that can anticipate a further time horizon. And evolution can be thought of an exploration of algorithms that persist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also the claim that “novelty comes from constraint” that I came across in some theoretical biology writings that’s been niggling for a number of years now. My model of what it means to understand something is to constrain/resolve the possibility space, so that there is less uncertainty/more (shannon) information of how to navigate the conceptual space effectively. And that’s typically how I operate, via constraints as opposed to working with a concrete model, which is how some friends describe how they work. The developer of wavefunction collapse commented that they initially tried an implemention of belief propagation, but found that constraint propagation worked better. This may be coincidence. Or not. I think there’s something relevant there to how a trained neural network/transformer works. Neural networks as supposedly universal function approximators (according fast.ai, I believe), and in MacKay’s “Information Theory, Inference, and Learning Algorithms”, he suggests that ‘data modeling is data compression’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking more on constraint, I recently read “A Thousand Brains” by Jeff Hawkins, where there is an aside to explain why the author thinks he can be relatively confident about a theory without doing confirmatory experiments – I find it a relatable explanation to how I operate, which is where you collect a lot of observations, especially seemingly paradoxical ones (‘constraints’), so that you develop a hyperparametric constraint on what a good answer looks like. With more constraints, there are relatively fewer explanations that can fit them all. So when you see one that can fits them all, it is very unusual and notable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So having read a decent amount of interesting theoretical frameworks about complex systems, especially biological ones, I’ve been on the lookout for good opportunities to try to develope better intuitions about them. And I guess this is why this arguably isn’t my first time around, as I tried to dissect Growing Neural Cellular Automata towards the end of 2020, where I found axis orientation in its first PCs (seems obvious in retrospect, but reminded me of embryology and Hox genes) but got distracted with graduate work and was sad that each ‘cell’ was not selfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this seemed like an unusually good fit given these various considerations. A short list of some things I’ve found interesting so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the phenomena of backup heads, copy suppression, self-repair (resilience, redundancy, constraint)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;training dynamics; what is the process of learning; the phenomena of grokking (embryology and developing, evolution)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am not excited by SAEs for some reason. My post-hoc rationalization is that it is a tool to understand what’s going on with these models, but is not really a self-organizing phenomena of these machine learning models themself, and I am more intrigued by questions around the fundamental behavior/principles of how and what these architectures self-organize information. So it’s interesting as a tool to help answer these questions, but is not really interesting as a main object/question of focus. E.g. I expect I’d develop interest if it seems like it can help me understand the above phenomena.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit too lazy right now to make these associations explicit, but I’m writing this down to messily gesture to these intuitions (and invest in a future opportunity to be self-satisfied). And I guess we’ll see how far this’ll go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/tEPHGZAb63dfq2v8n/how-useful-is-mechanistic-interpretability&quot;&gt;“Is mech interp useful?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m rather surprised that people question this because it is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more theoretically tractable than biology; I’d say the main difference is that biology has had much more time to establish itself. My impression is that mech interp is &lt;em&gt;easier&lt;/em&gt; than biology, and because biology is accepted as useful despite its logistically difficulties, there’s no clear reason to me that mech interp can’t get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A high level concern here is that there might be a lot of neurons which look roughly like french neurons and they can’t all be doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m reminded of “A thousand brains”’s metaphor of how it’s a group of people who know how a city’s water system works, that one person does not know all the details on their own, and there is overlapping knowledge such that if one or several people call out sick, the system will not immediately fail. And then in this metaphor, are there useful questions that can then be translated back to a mech interp context?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Current work seems very far from being useful (it isn’t currently useful) or explaining much what’s going on inside of models in key cases. But it’s hard to be very confident that a new field won’t work! And things can be far from useful, but become useful via slowly becoming more powerful, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This a weird take in my opinion, because this is the character of basic research. I’m obviously biased, but this feels like an overconfidence on known knowns and unknowns, and not enough of what is unknown. This guy sounds like a habitual exploiter, and not familiar with exploratory heuristics. Perhaps an anology would be that this is a similar difference to how a clinician and scientist approach biomedical questions. He is rather top down, interested in applications (AI safety, which I do not yet know how to muster any care about), whereas scientists tend to be more bottom up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do models plan?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in planning by means of the afoementioned anticipatory systems. However, as a first impression, I am not confident it has sufficient ability in that direction for me to be interested in doing a serious dive on it. I associate planning with exploration of counterfactuals, and I am not aware of a mechanism by which LLMs can do thhis. I would guess it would need a ‘meta-loop’ of modeling its options and a higher-level optimization goal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When I brought up the idea that i was considering a pivot into mech interp, my closest friends were baffled. It seemed like quite the nonsequitor, even flighty, said one friend. Which was surprising for me, because the connection seemed obvious, but then again, I tend to model the outside perspective poorly. Another of those friends had previously said that it took time to learn that my seemingly random tangents are usually not actually random, it’s just that I tend to explain the connection poorly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">stack ranking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/stack_rankings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="stack ranking" /><published>2023-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/stackrank</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/stack_rankings">&lt;p&gt;For some reason, it hadn’t been immediately obvious, or it wasn’t salient, that people’s differences can be framed as a difference in stack ranking. Technically this could just be called ‘priorities’, but somehow this aspect falls to the background with this term, at least for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People rarely disagree that values are good; this is perhaps tautological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference/contention is in the stack rank, of when tradeoffs are inevitable and there are hard decisions to make – and then in such contexts, which do you choose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is often not whether it is important, but what is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the inclination for this kind of thinking is a personality thing, I vaguely recall commiserating with someone of how I used to imagine emergency/disaster scenarios as a kid for fun, to explore what I actually cared about, of what I should direct my attention to when where you apply attention to is high stakes. I see this similarly with budgeting, of when you have financial constraint, what has greatest ROI in that context? I’m not exactly sure why, but people don’t seem to usually think of tradeoffs/opportunity cost. Maybe they don’t like considering constraint? Perhaps they find optimization problems tiring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably a coincidence, but it’s interesting how it’s the opposite with interpersonal optimization: social status is often seen as a zero-sum game, so people optimize for relative wealth; they don’t mind having less absolute wealth if it means that increases the hierarchical distance with their competitors/peers (where they’re on top, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addendum [2024/02/15]:
Regarding zero sum games vs positive sum games (we will ignore negative sum games because they seem not fun and because we can):
I think this framework mostly makes sense assuming this is a zero sum context. i.e. assuming that your time is finite, your money is finite (because you’re lazy like me and not good at earning more money) – people know how to optimize zero-sum games, so why do they not apply it here? What is the more prevailing framework(s)?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For some reason, it hadn’t been immediately obvious, or it wasn’t salient, that people’s differences can be framed as a difference in stack ranking. Technically this could just be called ‘priorities’, but somehow this aspect falls to the background with this term, at least for me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a hypothesis about lsd</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/lsd" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a hypothesis about lsd" /><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/lsd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/lsd">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;generalizations from n=1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, recreational drugs tend to not work as advertised on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also am able to do things sober that people take drugs for, like stay up late, introspect, feel socially relaxed, etc. When I do take drugs, it’s mostly for the curiosity for how it changes how you think – besides that I find no other upside. This is apparently odd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder how much is physiological (like hardware, i.e. how many drug-relevant receptors I have) versus psychological (like software i.e. apparently non-stubborn people do better with dementia because they’re more amenable to having their reality corrected).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alcohol probably skews towards a hardware difference. Alcohol is skewed towards the side effects with little to no fun effects. I suspect I have efficient alcohol to aldehyde (causes the unwanted side effects) conversion, and slow aldehyde to acetic acid (non-toxic end product) conversion; I can get a headache from a shot of beer and can really only get tipsy (which mostly feels like being tired) with liquor/high alcohol percentage. I might as well get sleepy and loopy withh no side effects. [Edit 2023/12/21: I can apparently also get side effects with ‘non-alcoholic alcochol’ (&amp;lt;0.5% alcohol)]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caffeine I’m not as sure of – it does not seem to help me concentrate/focus better. I drink it for the taste: I like that it’s hot, a strong bitter flavor that is nice to sip slowly as I do work (sweet drinks I tend to down; cold liquids make me distractingly cold and uncomfortable, and hot water is boring). Drinking too much caffeine can make me jittery and unable to sleep though, so it’s similar to alcohol in that its neegative side effects are more salient to me, with little to no observed positive effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LSD is commonly advertised to be life-changing, inspirational, etc. As someone generally interested in perspective shifts, I was intrigued. And I guess it was interesting, mostly on a meta-level. I took it with a close friend who also enjoys meta-analyzing things, and our sitter, who has sat others on acid-trips, was baffled that we were still doing it on acid. Apparently it’s not a thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended taking 1.5x the standard dose because it did not seem to be doing much with one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some takes that I have not seen described elsewhere (not that I’ve put much effort to look):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I thought the visual hallucinations/patterns were quickly boring; it’s like watching one of those 90’s screensavers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I suspect that LSD is associated with insight because it lowers your resolution of thought. And so instead getting caught up with the details (‘this makes me feel frustrated, anxious, hopeful, etc’, various multidimensional considerations), you round it (‘do I like it or not, yes/no’), and tada, a clear answer!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am not sure how to explain this without sounding pretentious, but I think I also understand people make more sense now – I think they’re normally operating on larger thought ‘blocks’. Because my resolution of thought decreased, my mind would jump to conclusions that I’ve been previously baffled by when I saw it in others (‘how did they get all the way over there??’). But it’s kind of like automated TV tropes, and social narrative arcs are completed for you. It’s interesting that there was this separate ‘curator’ in my head that was working overtime to try to correct my thoughts to be more precise and nuanced (trying get to 8.8 when your thought blocks are integers – ‘it’s more than 8!’,’so 9?’,’no, less than 9!’,’…8?, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relatedly, social interactions seem more automatically ‘colored’ with emotion – I got the sense my friend was annoyed at me even though historically I’ve never gotten that impression and with time, I realized that was an incorrect interpretation. I wonder if emotion is clearer with larger thought blocks because they implicitly convey a narrative arc, which is harder to convey with smaller thought blocks, f it is ‘chopped up’ too much.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can see why it’s something to do with friends because you can be more suggestible – you are on automatic at longer intervals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, LSD seems to decrease your resolution of thought, so that a stimulus tends to trigger a longer automated prediction stream. This goes with fewer opportunites for control/decisions, and a regression towards more normal behavior (the possibility space is smaller if there are fewer degrees of freedom).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m am not confident this is the best interpretation of my experience, but my friend who likes meta-analyzing said that his experience agreed with my model of it. So, here it is on the internet, in case someone has a similar experience and want solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">generalizations from n=1</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">your aesthetic is god</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/god" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="your aesthetic is god" /><published>2023-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/aesthetic_is_god</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/god">&lt;p&gt;I am itching to note these thoughts somewhere because I think I’ve resolved an interesting, long-standing gap in my understanding (and if it was obvious to you let me know how you learned it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I recently realized that I’ve been procrastinating on this because it touches on some presumably touchy subjects (e.g. God, God and irreverence, God and mechanistic explanations, God, and God, etc), and due to a chronic under-modeling of others, I am not confident that I’ll handle them gracefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…which becomes a motivation to write – let’s risk a splendid catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first observation: ‘God’ seems to be a conflated term. My, your, their God, “God”, and Gods, etc – people get it sufficiently wrong we’re inspired to correct them with a partcular enthusiasm. Like the British who talk about ‘them Europeans versus us’, for Christians, there’s other Christians, and then there’s us &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; Christians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in an agnostic/atheist family, but have been in proximity to Christian communities (I went to Vacational Bible School in the summers, probably as cheap daycare). In high school, I read the Selfish Gene, and impressed by this framework of evolution, then puzzled by the continued existence of Creationism, because it seemed obviously worse, I explored the question of why people believe what they do. And as I read around the topic, I developed the impression that science and organized religion were mostly mutually exclusive; with science you should no longer need religion. I did not think too hard about scientists who believed in a God, because I was mainly concerned with mainstream Christian notion of God, and my impression was that their notion of God was more on the ‘spiritual’ side, whatever that means. The point here is, whatever they were calling God did not mean the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, more than a decade later, I was reminded of this interesting phenomena through this &lt;a href=&quot;https://guzey.com/people-re-god/&quot;&gt;Alexey’s recent blog post&lt;/a&gt;, on this seeming paradox of religious scientists. But now I have a speculation of why that is – I serendipitously talked to someone about their religious experience, and serendipitously encountered the thought, ‘I think I relate to this’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just that, instead of ‘God’, I’ve been calling it ‘aesthetic’. And with this consideration, I’m now wondering if they maybe &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; all trying to gesture to the same thing after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I don’t mean to claim that all religious/spiritual people are necessarily gesturing to the same thing when they think of God – as a kid, I took everything at face value and &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; God never talked to me. But I’m suspecting that there is sometimes a convergence with a certain kind of religious.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-option of the term ‘aesthetic’ arose some years ago, after I attended an academic conference and found that I didn’t know how to describe my relative disinterest in various presentations and posters. I could not identify anything wrong with their scientific approach. The closest explanation I could come up with was that they weren’t ‘pretty’ enough. And surprisingly, this explanation stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered that I related to the experience of artists, where they are compelled to search for, collect, and create things that inspire, to attempt to express their intuitions. But instead of beautiful paintings or sculptures, it is looking to create beautiful models – if so, science could be driven by more subjectivity than I originally thought. And then I started to use it everywhere to gesture to low-level preferences, basic gut feelings, anywhere to express the sense and intuition of when something is beautiful or satisfying. This is what a subset of scientists mean by God, I suspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[But while your gut can tell you whether something is ‘aesthetic’ or not, it does not tell you why. And so to find and/or build more aesthetic things, it can be a scientific process of its own, with hypothesis generation and testing.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;III.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the relationship between aesthetic and the religious-religious God?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fascinatingly speculative book called “The Origins of Consciousness and the Breakdown of the Bicameral Mind” by Julian Jaynes. It proposes that consciousness is a cultural phenomena, that people used to literally hear God’s voices and that has come to be understood/modeled as our ‘own’ voice. It is not something that is easily proven, so why is Julian Jaynes’ book worth reading? It submits for consideration the idea that people might’ve modeled and thus experienced their consciousness differently. And now, it’s provided the inspiration for the adjacent consideration that one’s internal experience is culturally malleable, and perhaps &lt;em&gt;even today&lt;/em&gt;, people model their consciousness differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, what does being religious entail? Prayer, being devout, going to church, having faith, surrendering to God, etc. Are there secular analogues to such practices? My prior impressions were ‘no, not really’. My current impressions are more conspiratorial:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started with prayer. I had found serendipitously found myself joining a small group (for old times’ sake) and during group prayers, where people reflected on the problems in their life, things they were grateful for, and well wishes they had for others, it struck me that this was similar to what I do when introspecting. And suddenly, prayer didn’t seem like a polite, black-box ritual – I could concretely see how it could be functional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, what is introspection but praying to your aesthetic to figure out a problem and asking it for guidance? I’m not sure if this generalizes to others, but that’s basically what it is for me. And then if you don’t introspect/pray for a while, you’re less in touch with your aesthetic/God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then in unpacking what at least one person means by ‘surrendering’ (to Jesus), it maps well to my understanding of making your actions consistent with your values – you make your life consistent with your aesthetic. And if you keep following your aesthetic/God, you develop faith – you may not know where it’ll take you, and it may be contrary to common/external advice, but you develop trust that there’s something real there, and that following it tends to lead to good outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am wondering if religion can be seen as a tool society/culture has devised to teach introspection en mass. I’ve also started to suspect that introspection doesn’t come naturally to many (after talking around topics of mental frameworks/organization, someone once asked me ‘So, what drugs do you use?’, and in reading a draft of &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github.io/poop/personal_statement.md&quot;&gt;my personal statement&lt;/a&gt;, a mentor commented, ‘you think a lot don’t you?’). And that’s why prayer isn’t the only tool; ‘woo-y’ practices like manifestation, horoscopes, etc are also beginning to look like tools for introspecting to me; I think they can work because they can prime/load into your mind certain questions and/or attitudes, making you better situated to find possible solutions (like confirmation bias or frequency illusion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think this is why post-rats tend to be into manifestation and crystals: a common error rationalists tend to fall into is overriding their sense of aesthetic; it’s perhaps following the trope of hubris, of thinking themselves above God. Then, post-rats are those who’ve felt the repercussions of that and are now looking to be closer to their aesthetic/God (but I have a pet-peeve dislike of the term ‘vibes’ – I think its because they gesture to feelings/aesthetic – and stop there. I’m arguing here that feelings are important (see tenet 1 of &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github.io/poop/water&quot;&gt;‘shared norms’&lt;/a&gt;) but they often require critical analysis/processing to be used well – e.g. there’s something sparkly here, but &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is it sparkly?  maybe why bible study is important?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not fully explored this mapping between aesthetic and God yet, but I feel like I’ve been able to take it farther than I initially expected – one last one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I had trouble understanding why people fell into depressive nihilism (mentioned in some previous post), and watching &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Everything_Everywhere_All_at_Once&quot;&gt;EEAAO&lt;/a&gt; made it more salient as a pervasive problem. My own reaction to realizing that nothing matters was ‘great, that means I can fully focus/decide to do what I want’. While I wouldn’t claim that I fully understand it even now, I’ve since developed the tentative hypothesis that the difference between others’ and my reaction is that I have a strong sense of things mattering to me (see &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github.io/eat&quot;&gt;input&lt;/a&gt;); I was saved by my aesthetic. Or, dare we say – “I was saved by God”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-joking continued, if your aesthetic is God, ‘you have God on your side’/God is with you’/’the power of Christ compels you’, or whatever is empowering – maybe use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;V.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some remaining thoughts and questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally believe by default that people make sense, according to their framework, and while I am not yet confident this above exposition isn’t some spurious mapping, I think it’d help to find people with religious frameworks be more concretely relatable. Because it seems like despite different starting points, they seem to have converged in pointing to the same thing – and why is that? Why does it seem so essential? Or rediscovered often?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one develop a sense of ideals, or find their aesthetic? Why are some people more idealistic than others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mainstream approach to religion is like high school english class for me; they feel like a bastardization of something I actually find meaningful and substantial years later, like this angle and insightful video essays, respectively. 
So perhaps for a future exploration: On building cathedrals, or how to find God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to AG and BT for reading.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books that contributed to the development of this framework:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Origin-Consciousness-Breakdown-Bicameral-Mind/dp/0618057072&quot;&gt;“The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of the Bicameral Mind” (Julian Jaynes)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Artists-Way-25th-Anniversary/dp/0143129252&quot;&gt;“The Artist’s Way” (Juila Cameron)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am itching to note these thoughts somewhere because I think I’ve resolved an interesting, long-standing gap in my understanding (and if it was obvious to you let me know how you learned it).</summary></entry></feed>