<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-25T01:40:56-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">some forays around cancer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/intro_cancer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="some forays around cancer" /><published>2023-09-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/intro_cancer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/intro_cancer">&lt;p&gt;A friend recently reached out to ask my thoughts on cancer treatments for a terminally ill family member ‘because I know biology’. And I realized that despite all my years in biomedical research, I had very little to say; I know surprisingly little about cancer. I guess it’s kind of like asking a software engineer why your computer doesn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it’s an interesting gap (chasm?) in knowledge, and unsurprising: Off the top of my head, I’ve only read two books about cancer: “Emperor of All Maladies” and “The Selfish Cell” – so let’s rectify that a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some initial gaps in my understanding that seem interesting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why do larger animals not have a higher rate of cancer?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pediatric vs adult cancer – are there trends in how they arise?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are there underlying principles regarding the types of cancers that tend to arise from the different tissue/organ systems?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how do various cancer treatments purportedly work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;immuno-oncology: how much of cancer incidences involve oversight/dysregulation of the immune system?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what can cancer tell you about multicellular self-organization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I anticipate these being rabbit-holes that don’t have obvious endpoints, so I’ll artificially constrain it to ‘how much I can find out in an arbitrary week’ (note: due to procrastination, it turned into two weeks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-initial-dive&quot;&gt;An initial dive:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-why-do-larger-animals-not-have-a-higher-rate-of-cancer&quot;&gt;1. why do larger animals not have a higher rate of cancer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve actually come across an answer to this before, but I apparently didn’t learn it well because the vague answer in my head doesn’t feel fully coherent. It might’ve been something related to cancer having difficulty taking over the greater mass of a larger organism. (ah, my memory is excellent, it was from an episode of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D1HFP84RXak&amp;amp;ab_channel=SciShow&quot;&gt;SciShow&lt;/a&gt;, and the concept I’m thinking of is hypertumors –  it seems like it’s a controversial hypothesis though.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question seems encompassed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peto%27s_paradox&quot;&gt;Peto’s Paradox&lt;/a&gt;, the observation that the incidence of cancer between species doesn’t seem to correspond to their number of cells or lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3060950/&quot;&gt;decent review&lt;/a&gt; that goes through a good number of hypotheses, mostly to conclude that they haven’t been really tested yet so the mechanism is still pretty unknown. But as a sampling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypertumors are a consideration. But they’d expect areas of necrosis, which aren’t really seen. 
There may be an evoulationary tradeoff like reduced fertility (evidence?). 
Larger organisms have a lower metabolic rate – does this lead to lowered free radical damage from oxygen? Or does this create a less competitive environment?
They seem to have increased tumor suppressor genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do whales and elephants have the same or analagous mechanisms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if constitutively increasing the expression of tumor antigen TP53 increased suppression ability in mice increased tumor suppression ability, it seemed to also increase their rate of aging – why is that? It’s slightly ironic that aging is associated with increased cancer risk, but increasing tumor suppressing gene expression leads to premature aging (hmm looks like a tradeoff).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;status: still kind of not sure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-pediatric-vs-adult-cancer--are-there-trends-in-how-they-arise&quot;&gt;2. pediatric vs adult cancer – are there trends in how they arise?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pediatric cancer is a developmental disease” – in &lt;em&gt;Origins of Order&lt;/em&gt;, Kauffman suggests considering cancer as a ‘disease of differentiation’, but when I asked a professor who had thought a lot about the evolution of cancer for her research, she said that the current thought is that cancer is moreso a de novo adaptation than an ataavism towards a more stem-like cell type. But perhaps Kauffman’s suggestion may be more true for pediatric cancers (new question: what can they tell us about the origins of new cell types?). Because they are moreso caused by ‘disorganization’ than adapatation, they have lower mutational burden, though with broader epigenetic dysregulation (and epigenetics are where cell types are distinguished). (Some intriguing bio tidbits I’ve filed away are the observations that there are some cancers that seem to be &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;fully epigenetic&lt;/a&gt; and that it seems possible to take a (specific) cancer and have it functionally integrate with embryonic cells to become a viable organism.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be associated with the greater incidence of fusion genes, but I don’t really have any idea of how fusion genes work right now and why it’d relate to cancer (second new question: are there principles underlying how and which genes can recombine?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common pediatric cancers are leukemia, central nervous system tumors, neuroblastomas, and teratomas; an underlying trend is that pediatric cancers tend to have a nonepithelial origin, originating from stem or progenitor cells during a particular time window (third question: what makes them diverge in the first place? how does the time window affect their phenotype/prognosis? why did they become cancers and not, say, a conjoined twin?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, adult cancers are generally of epithelial origin (carcinomas apparently account for 90% of cancers). This seems to be related to the higher turnover in these tissues, as they tend to interface with the environment. The most common adult cancers are in the lung, prostate, breast, colon, and pancreas, and sensibly, lung and colon cancers are associated with environmental stressors – most lung cancer cases are related to smoking, and most colon cancer cases are preceded by inflammatory gut problems. I am not sure why skin cancers aren’t as high up. Instead we have prostate and breast cancer, which can be categorized as the hormonally-driven cancers. And pancreatic cancer, which is just so insidious that despite relatively low incidence, its high mortality puts it up there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different treatment/intervention considerations for pediatric versus adult cancers, particularly given their different etiologies. For neuroblastomas in particular, it is expected that some will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5920563/&quot;&gt;spontaneously regress&lt;/a&gt;, and no intervention is needed. And because pediatric cancers tend to arise an earlier developmental time window (as early as !), these cancer cells tend to retain fetus-specific antigens that are (relatively) absent from postnatal tissues, so you can easily target them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pediatric cancers tend to have lower recurrence but have a higher concern for long-term side effects, mostly because they’re still developing, but also that their cancers tend to be treated more aggressively (fourth question: why?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6631320/
https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/full/10.1146/annurev-cancerbio-070620-091632&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;status: decent broad stroke understanding, but limited second-order understanding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-are-there-underlying-principles-regarding-the-types-of-cancers-that-tend-to-arise-from-the-different-tissueorgan-systems&quot;&gt;3. are there underlying principles regarding the types of cancers that tend to arise from the different tissue/organ systems?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you google ‘the most common cancers’, they tend to list them by organ type, i.e. lung, skin. But for this question I think it’s more informative to distinguish them by cell type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in adults, the most cancers are epithelial in origin, aka carcinomas. This seems to be due to higher exposure to environmental insults and turnover (the cells that interface with the envrionment are usually epithelial), facilitating greater mutation and adaptation (smoking seems associated with 85% of lung cancer cases). This gives greater opportunity for chronic inflammation, which contributes to the description of tumors as ‘wounds that never heal’. This chronic inflammation is bad because it causes oxidate stress and subsequent DNA damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across metabolic reprogramming in sepsis, and there’s this concept called immune paralysis, where you have both hyperinflammation and immunosuppression. Specifically, the normal state of oxphos is stimulated into aerobic glycolysis through (hyper)inflammation, which leads to the generation of lactic acid, which leads to the next metabolic adaptation to FAO, which corresponds to an immunosuppressive phenotype. “Therefore, limiting the glycolysis pathway can reduce organ damage caused by an “inflammation storm” in the early stage of sepsis.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In shorthand, immune paralysis: hyperinflammation and immunosuppression
hyperinflammation; oxphos -&amp;gt; aerobic glycolysis -&amp;gt; lactic acid -&amp;gt; immunosuppression (FAO)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been exposed to the pH sensor GPR65 which seems to have some role in evoking the inflammatory response. It seems that GPR65 KO mice do better in DSS experiments perhaps because they have a higher inflammatory response at baseline, but worse in sepsis models. Perhaps the inability to sense pH changes alter this metabolic reprogramming trajectory in sepsis, for worse?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breast and prostate cancers tend to be ‘hormonal’ cancers. It seems that it’s because they’re naturally sensitive to hormones, and hormones can act as growth factors, increasing the rate of cell division. I am not sure why this is a relatively fragile mechanism, in that I’d then expect cancers that are dependent on other growth factors i.e. HGH or IGF. Or what about other conditions that control growth, e.g. diabetes, obesity, other metabolic disorders? It seems that diabetes does increase the risk of cancer (due to what mechanism?), as does obesity, but the mechanism seems to be more related to an increased baseline of chronic inflammation than increased available energy to cells, as I first speculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that takes us back to chronic inflammation as a foundation for a lot of cancers. I am not sure why this doesn’t seem more heavily targeted, especially since cancer and aging are hot fields – I’m guessing it is not easy to address. Still, that makes my current project seem more well-positioned because failure to return from inflammation seems like a pervasive problem, especially with age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly tangential question is what makes certain cancers more deadly? A quick google search gives me ‘deadliest cancers/cancers with the lowest survival rate’:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pancreatic cancer, exocrine (make digestive enzymes) – hard to detect early, don’t respond as well to commonly used therapies, why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;brain (presuming hard to treat bc of location)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;small cell lung cancer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mesotheliomas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gallbladder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;esophageal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this made me realize what I meant to ask is ‘what makes certain cancers have a more aggressive phenotype?’ Being hard to detect and/or hard to treat is orthogonal to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10038208/&quot;&gt;metabolic reprogramming in sepsis&lt;/a&gt;
https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352304221001148&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Therefore, the essence of inflammation-targeting cancer therapy is how to accurately identify the type of inflammation and selectively promote cancer-inhibiting inflammation and inhibit cancer-promoting inflammation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;status: the main root causes of adult cancers seem to be related to 1) chronic inflammation, and 2) hormones – they seem worth delving into&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-how-do-various-cancer-treatments-purportedly-work&quot;&gt;4. how do various cancer treatments purportedly work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main treatment approaches to cancer seem to be: surgery, chemotherapy, and radiation. Actual treatments seems to often be some combination of them. Somehow, surgery and radiation seems sufficiently self-explanatory so I’ll focus on how various chemotherapies work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it seems they largely try to interfere with cell proliferation, whether it be at DNA, RNA, or protein synthesis level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess immunotherapy isn’t established enough to make it to standard practice considerations. But I think it is most intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because for all the local inflammation in tumours, in many cases the overall innate immunity of the host is blunted. There seems to be a kind of signalling confusion – can there be a cytokine/signaling reset like in atrial fibrillation? Not sure if this is an appropriate metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for the rare cases of spontaneous regression, many of them &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8271173/&quot;&gt;seem associated with a case of acute infection&lt;/a&gt;. How might acute infection affect these variables? Is it related at all to how CAR-T cells work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I don’t even understand well how CAR-T cells work. This feels slightly embarrassing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK564367/
https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6721818/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;status: there is a lot more material/depth to go into in this direction; I have a very superficial understanding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-immuno-oncology-how-much-of-cancer-incidences-involve-oversightdysregulation-of-the-immune-system-and-other-higher-level-regulatory-mechanisms-ie-metabolism&quot;&gt;5. immuno-oncology: how much of cancer incidences involve oversight/dysregulation of the immune system? and other higher-level regulatory mechanisms (i.e. metabolism?)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So cancers are salient and problematic when we get them, but why do most of us not have cancer, or more often? As I once wondered as a kid, given that there are single-gene diseases, why do we not randomly sprout tumors on our arms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our tissues generally have oxygen and nutrient limitations; cancers that are successful tend to acquire the ability to attract blood vessels. This is why most of us who die of old have cancers that won’t be the cause of our death; they grow too slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4471149/&quot;&gt;There’s this Science paper&lt;/a&gt; that suggests that cancer-driver-gene mutations are found in normal skin, so their presence is not sufficient to generate cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cases of sporadic regression preceded by acute infection suggests that the immune system may be capable of eliminating at least some cancers, given the right impetus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The means by which cancer evades the immune system is termed ‘immune escape’. Some discussed mechanisms include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;loss of antigenicity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;loss of immunogeneicity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;immunosuppresive microenvironment (myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs) and regulatory T cells (Treg) as well as cytokines, and acidic/toxic metabolites that inhibit activity of immune cells)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How might acute infection affect these variables? How do CAR-T cells try to address this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or just generally, how can these be regained?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu.2022.961805/full
https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4334715/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;status: there is something interesting here, but I didn’t go into sufficient depth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-what-can-cancer-tell-you-about-multicellular-self-organization&quot;&gt;6. what can cancer tell you about multicellular self-organization?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainly, that there are many ways to fail in multicellular self-organization; there seems to be parallels with societal (dys)function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some hallmarks of cancer cells, from an article titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3660034/&quot;&gt;“How cancer shapes evolution, and how evolution shapes cancer”&lt;/a&gt;:
(a) having self-sufficiency in growth signals, 
(b) loss of sensitivity to anti-growth signals, 
(c) loss of sensitivity to programmed cell suicide, 
(d) immortality (cells can divide forever), 
(e) altered metabolic properties, 
(f) higher mutation rates, 
(g) ability to attract blood vessels and (h) the capacity to invade tissues and become metastatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading it inversely, this is what evolution has given multicellular organisms a means of higher level control in order to work properly. So to develop a functional tissue, you need to be able to effectively control:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(a) exposure/response to growth signals
(b) anti-growth signals, 
(c) programmed cell suicide, 
(d) immortality, 
(e) metabolic properties, 
(f) determinism/predictability/standardization
(g) resources/nutrients
(h) specialization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some basic characteristics of cancer that I found interesting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;loss of density dependent inhibition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;autocrine growth stimulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;loss of contact inhibition via cell-cell or cell-matrix contact&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;defective differentiation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rabbit-holes that I think have potential to provide insight towards this question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What factors affect tumor maturity? Is there a trend in their trajectory of differentiation and maturity?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do cancer cells get incentivized towards dedifferentation and the EMT process?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are patterns of hypoxia within the tumor?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;status: not thought about deeply enough&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;concluding-thoughts&quot;&gt;Concluding thoughts:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now more intrigued by 1) the role and phenomena of chronic inflammation, and 2) how to think about system/’cultural’ control of multicellular systems. Though I kind of already thought the latter was interesting; my interest in the former is particularly piqued.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A friend recently reached out to ask my thoughts on cancer treatments for a terminally ill family member ‘because I know biology’. And I realized that despite all my years in biomedical research, I had very little to say; I know surprisingly little about cancer. I guess it’s kind of like asking a software engineer why your computer doesn’t work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to not learn a new concept; unexpected machine overconfidence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/overconfidence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to not learn a new concept; unexpected machine overconfidence" /><published>2023-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/overconfidence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/overconfidence">&lt;p&gt;What happens when we learn something new?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you learn a new concept, I think we start by using existing language to describe it. I think it was in Julian Jaynes’ “The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of the Bicameral Mind” that claimed that everything you understand is mostly metaphors upon metaphors. ‘This new thing is like X – but like Y in this aspect’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So can we help machines learn a new concept on their own?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, it’d possibly start by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;noticing something is weird (anomaly detection)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;looking for a pattern in how its weird&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make a new concept encompassing these weird patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To more concretely test this, what would happen if you trained a neural net on MNIST, and showed it a letter (‘A’, in this case)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/not_mnist.png&quot; title=&quot;not MNIST&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me reformat its guesses for you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first image, the numbers correspond to its confidence level for each conceptual option by position. They are all highly confident. At &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; 99.999994% confident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…why is it so confident? so &lt;em&gt;wrongly&lt;/em&gt; confidently??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought that I’d be able to at least tell it that ‘when there seems to be a trend in a certain mix between numbers, take note’. But it’s just so certain that it’s a number each time that I can’t utilize any sort of uncertainty to flag these letters as ‘odd’. It is currently unteachable – it believes that there is nothing for it to learn here. Nothing is weird, everything is fine, apparently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I need to probe deeper into how it arrived at these very confident-looking ‘decisions’. It’s probably a byproduct of the learning mechanism; I’m not sure how difficult of a fix it’d be yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the next steps are to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;find the source of its seeming certainty, and divest it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then we can actually start with anomaly detection, which was the first bottleneck I thought I’d encounter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also since there’s probably updates to image recognition now, I could look into what is currently state of the art and see if I encounter a similar problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What happens when we learn something new?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">thoughts on “Team of Rivals”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/lincoln" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="thoughts on “Team of Rivals”" /><published>2023-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/lincoln</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/lincoln">&lt;p&gt;I picked up “Team of Rivals” browsing through some shelves one night, in want of a compelling book. It was not completely random. I might’ve been motivated to read a biography when I was writing &lt;a href=&quot;narratives&quot;&gt;‘the practicality of frivolous stories’&lt;/a&gt;, and realizing that biographies would probably similarly inspire one on a narrative of ‘how to be’. And Lincoln in particular has a connotational halo in my head of someone who is of great moral character, a potential reference point for the question of ‘how to be’. I was not wrong. Also this title was primed because it has been on my book list since 2016/03/09 (I have self-indulgent, unnecessarily-detailed documentation), probably from a cardiothoracic surgeon named Nat (while it took more than seven years, the recommendation was not for nought).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find that “Team of Rivals” has many elements of an adventure story, with an underdog protagonist with humble beginnings, being scrappy and traveling long distances to make something of themself, and getting caught up in a war for an idealistic cause. I also associate ‘world building’ with fiction, so I was surprised to notice that here too has elements of world building that contextualize these characters. Though one thing “Team of Rivals” more effectively communicates is the prevalence of pestilence; the deaths of family and friends due to epidemics almost seem routine – I am now more salient of the impact of 20th century medicine. Otherwise, this is just a smaller, quaint world, a setting adjacent to adventure/steampunk stories, where there is greater sincerity in politics, more public involvement in politics, more willingness to stuff people on mattresses on pool tables whenever there is a large event, more bed sharing in general (there seems to be not enough beds), public accessibility to the White House and the President, more intimate male relationships where they write each other ardent letters of appreciation, and more letter writing in general (at least among our cast of characters). In the way I imagine old people reminisce about the times they memorized their loved ones’ phone numbers, I reminisce about the times where you could recognize your friends’ and families’ handwriting; there’s a certain romanticism to it. But at least it’s not all you have left of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Team of Rivals” largely feels like a character study. Interestingly, while I tend to have a loose assumption of ‘there are different tradeoffs with different personalities’, characters here are often compared with clear implicit judgment, ‘this guy did things better’. I guess that’s possible when you have their completed life to evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an abundance of idealism, ambition, competency, and empathy, but in the eponymous “Team of Rivals”, or Lincoln’s cabinet, Lincoln is the clear winner, and his rivals serve as foils. Bates, who became his Attorney General, had a lot of things going for him but was not as ambitious; he was content being at home with his large, happy family. Seward, his Secretary of State, is a near perfect candidate, whose perhaps one failing was that he was too complacent and insufficiently detail-oriented, at least relative to Lincoln. Salmon Chase, who became the Secretary of Treasury, I found to be one the more fascinating characters, as he was ambitious and idealistic enough to eventually become Chief Justice, and so competent he was cajoled to remain Secretary of Treasury through four? resignation letters despite pervasive self-righteousness and self-deception. Goodwin effectively illustrates through Chase how not to do ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also more minor character comparisons, including an amusing one between the generals McClellan and Grant. One who goes to the front with just an extra shirt, hairbrush, and toothbrush, and, and the other with multiple, heavy trunks. One constantly demurs requests to make military progress in a roundabout fashion (‘once I get enough people, conditions shall be suitable!’), and the other is known for such exchange:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Enemy (Buckner): ceasefire “and appointment of commissions to settle terms of capitulation”?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Grant: “No terms except unconditional and immediate surrender can be accepted” (418)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is meant to illustrate how ‘perfection is the enemy of progress’, but at the same time, I am not sure if I skimmed or if the book glossed over how McClellan came to be known as ‘young Napoleon’, which suggests that he had some level of perceived competency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I am not sure how skewed of a portrayal Lincoln has here, but I think of a justification from the book itself, where Lincoln comments on whether George Washington should be portrayed with or without blemish: “It makes human nature better to believe that one human being was perfect, that human perfection is possible” (152). And the Lincoln portrayed here evokes a practical implementation of Jesus. Lincoln had a bout with depression when his friends and first lover died from an epidemic, but was motivated out of it from “the desire to prove himself worthy, to be held in great regard, to win the veneration and respect of his fellow citizens”. This is not an unusual ambition, I think. And while laudable, neither is his higher goal, “to afford all, an unfettered start, and a fair chance in the race of life” (367); his rivals had similar levels of idealism. But I think it is common to do ambition distastefully (see: Chase), and how he implemented such goals is of particular note and inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expected that Lincoln is competent, and he very much is: He was a self-taught learner (“The books, and your capacity for understanding them, are just the same in all places…Always bear in mind that your own resolution to succeed is more important than any other thing.” (84)) without the privileged upbringing of his rivals, with constant consideration of others’ thoughts (Weed: “Lincoln sees all, listens to all, speaks with all, reads all, but thinks and acts by himself, for himself” (289)), but with his own well-developed sense of aesthetic; he embodies “luck favors the prepared”. This is very satisfyingly illustrated with the editing of his First Inaugural Address, where he takes seriously Seward’s suggestions, and makes it better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/lincoln_better_angels.jpg&quot; title=&quot;better angels&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another of Lincoln’s speeches, he concludes with the inspirational command, “Let us have faith that right makes might, and in that faith, let us, to the end, dare to do our duty as we understand it” (232). I am not sure that this guideline provides sufficient nuance, as this appears to be a principle that Chase also follows, with less tasteful outcomes. I think the difference is in Lincoln’s ability to get to the deeper core of a value – I suspect it is related to his tendency to take the longer view of things. In an interview with Goodwin: “He wanted to accomplish something that would stand the test of time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the motivation, this is illustrated in how he communicates, choosing to distill ideas with metaphors that are accessible to the everyday man, rather than the flowery, abstract metaphors typical of the well-read – he understands that a goal of a speech is to communicate broadly, not just to impress your colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had depth and consistency to his empathy. ‘[H]e had observed that it was the nature of man, when told he should be ‘shunned and despised’…to retreat within himself, close all the avenues to his head and heart’ (168), and said that he ‘could not condemn the South for an ability to end slavery when he himself knew of no easy solution’ (699). I have found this aesthetic in modern peers and friends, but it is still non-standard enough that I was pleased to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even rarer still, I think, is his ‘profound and elevated sense of ambition’: “notably free of pettiness, malice, and overindulgence”; “though Lincoln desired success as freely as any of his rivals, he did not allow his quest for office to consume the kindness and openheartedness with which he treated supporters and rivals alike” (256). This is effectively illustrated in the case of Lincoln giving his 47 votes to his same-platform rival Trumbull (who had 5 votes that he would not give up) so that his anti-Nebraska platform could have the majority and win the senator seat. What is particularly satisfying is that this local sacrifice would win him loyalties that would later help him win the election. His ego-less attitude (and self-confidence) is also why Lincoln’s cabinet as a “Team of Rivals” exists at all: “I had looked the party over and concluded that these were the very strongest men. Then I had no right to deprive the country of their services” (319). And if somehow these are insufficient, his magnanimity is gratuitously illustrated throughout the book in his patience with Chase. This is how you do ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these traits, his ambition, his idealism, his competence, his empathy, his magnanimity, additionally compounded by Lincoln’s lively sense of humor (Lincoln’s witty quip in his own dream: ‘The Lord prefers common-looking people, that is the reason he makes so many of them’ (593)) and optimism (“allow by-gones to be by-gones, and to look to the present and future only” (272)), come together to depict such a great figure that, by the time Edward Stanton says, ‘Now he belongs to the ages’ (743) upon Lincoln’s death, you can viscerally feel the loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s okay if it takes &lt;del&gt;four score and&lt;/del&gt; seven years to get around to reading it. I don’t regret not reading it earlier. But here is a recommendation, just in case you find yourself in want of a compelling book, of both compelling narrative and a particularly compelling character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;comments solicited, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1uQzH2Y-rImId2z7CW8yG0mfgmxVA83dsrCIMzzVirjM/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;kludgey comment-able form here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I picked up “Team of Rivals” browsing through some shelves one night, in want of a compelling book. It was not completely random. I might’ve been motivated to read a biography when I was writing ‘the practicality of frivolous stories’, and realizing that biographies would probably similarly inspire one on a narrative of ‘how to be’. And Lincoln in particular has a connotational halo in my head of someone who is of great moral character, a potential reference point for the question of ‘how to be’. I was not wrong. Also this title was primed because it has been on my book list since 2016/03/09 (I have self-indulgent, unnecessarily-detailed documentation), probably from a cardiothoracic surgeon named Nat (while it took more than seven years, the recommendation was not for nought).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to not be a conspiracy theorist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/independently" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to not be a conspiracy theorist" /><published>2023-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/independent-thinking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/independently">&lt;p&gt;I generally enjoy reading Paul Graham’s essays, but when I first read his essay on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/think.html&quot;&gt;independent thinking&lt;/a&gt; in Nov 2020, I admittedly found it a little bit frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting – well-written as usual. It was validating, as it describes what I’m doing right. But in my self-absorbed way, the way he went about blithely extolling the virtues of independent thinking while I was dealing with problems that arose from this very independent thinking was pettily but profoundly irritating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graham talks about how one might become more independent-minded, and the first one, ‘to be unaware of conventions’ (or, for want of powers of perception), is how I unknowingly took the independent minded route. And, justified by my lack of choice in the matter, I would like to complain about it: It is good to aspire to be better than the sheep, but at least sheep are generally about average – with being independent, there is the real pitfall of being &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; than average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends would know, as they gleefully keep a list of my ‘surprisingly basic’ failings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am not particularly concerned with trying to think independently because I do not find it hard to think independently. I succeed with flying colors. But I think it is hard to think independently &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an attempt to address what my younger self would’ve wanted to read about at the time. Because once upon a time, I was mirred in a mild crisis of self-doubt. I would like to not be in this situation and it was rather painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Graham’s essay came out, I had been struggling to integrate with the biology of aging field for the past two years, and not being able to make it sit comfortably – I could consciously follow why people think this is cool, but I could not emotionally relate (maybe because I am very okay with the idea of my own mortality). Many in the aging field are satisfied with answers that I feel is not sufficiently satisfactory, but I was having difficulty making headway in a direction that I felt was more compelling. It was like arriving at an answer that differs from the majority of people – naturally, being a more unconfident sort, I suspected I had a miscalculation somewhere, but I couldn’t figure it out. I found that there is a loneliness in being out of sync with people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been listening to the portal podcast around that time (perhaps specifically “40: Introducing The Portal Essay Club - What if everyone is simply insane?” on Apple Podcasts) and it occurred to me that this is what an insane person might think. Arguably, insane means a critical distance from your norm, and so it is relative, possibly mutually perceived. In the same week, I happened to meet a conspiracy theorist. He sounded pretty reasonable, like a critical thinker, with some takes that question the norm. It wasn’t until he started commenting on the areas I was well-versed in that I realized that his takes were probably worse than default. I thought of “A Beautiful Mind”, a horror film that bills itself as ‘drama’ – it is horrifying to be in a situation where you can’t trust your sense of reality. You can question the herd, do things your way, and be worse – you could be a conspiracy theorist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PG’s internal structure for independent thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;fastidiousness about truth&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;resistance to being told what to think&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;curiosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(I think if I were a conspiracy theorist, I would think that I have all of these things.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, it was then easy to draw the lines between conspiracy theorizing and my critical thoughts about the aging field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/January_6_United_States_Capitol_attack&quot;&gt;the Jan 6th Capitol attack&lt;/a&gt;, which was not helpful at all in this regard. A turning point was watching CNN coverage of the capital storming, and the news anchor going, ‘this is not the America we know’ in a ‘I’m surprised by your bad behavior – you should know better and I’m very disappointed in you’ kind of tone. My internal reaction to that was, ‘isn’t that your job? to keep a finger on things that are happening throughout America and be able to provide useful commentary on why we’re seeing what we’re seeing? This is admitting your failing as a newsperson if this is not the America you know, because that means your models are wrong and you should correct them – what are you going to do about it??’ This was a new low on the unreliability of established media outlets. It took some time for my strong criticism to propogate through my accultured sense of media authority, but it did, and the best way I can currently describe the feeling is a sense of disconnect with the mainstream narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself distrusting large groups of people, groups that are perceived to have authority, how do you develop a stable sense of reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was sufficiently overwhelmed, I went to my close friends, and received reassurance and future insurance/assurance: the solution to this problem is friends. Not just any good friend, but friends that are good at critical thinking in a way that you admire (what if you have bad taste in what is good taste?&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;). You want friends that will be frank with you and tell you what they think (and you should try your best to adopt an attitude that makes them willing to do so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things eventually got better. In summer 2021, a friend recommended ‘Edison as I knew him’, citing this particular passage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“That bang on the table was worth worlds to me. No man up to then had given me any encouragement. I had hoped that I was headed right, sometimes I knew that it was, sometimes I only wondered if I was”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And somehow it was grounding to get an example that it is normal to have doubts, and it is important to seek those who can encourage you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that independent thinking, ironically, is best done with the help of others. Graham does note this, that you should find independent-thinking friends to talk to, but I think it’s moreso framed in the context of being exposed to unconventional thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think if you’re anything like me, a particular value of friends is so that your attempt at independent thinking doesn’t take a bad turn. In the end, reality is rather local, and who you are, how you perceive, is shaped by those near you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/i_at_the_center.png&quot; title=&quot;I at the Center&quot; style=&quot;width=&amp;quot;400&amp;quot;; height:600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;font-size: 12px&quot;&gt;[1] I&apos;m sorry, I haven&apos;t thought that far -- find better friends? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;comments solicited, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1jF0s0IVLF338Uvgy1RKo4P8roP7ESnwwJGbsBUhwcGQ/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;kludgey comment-able form here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I generally enjoy reading Paul Graham’s essays, but when I first read his essay on independent thinking in Nov 2020, I admittedly found it a little bit frustrating.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the practicality of frivolous stories</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/narratives" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the practicality of frivolous stories" /><published>2023-07-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/narratives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/narratives">&lt;p&gt;In high school I transitioned from reading a lot of fantasy/adventure to reading nonfiction, like “The Selfish Gene”, “Mutants”, “The Checklist Manifesto”, etc. I remember it was hard – it turned out that I had unconsciously developed the habit of skim-reading, because fantasy/adventure novels tend to have a lot of descriptions that can evoke mental imagery without careful reading. This did not work for the nonfiction I read. I’d go through the motions of reading several pages and not absorb anything I read. I slowly unlearned this habit by keeping a piece of computer paper folded up into quarters as a bookmark, and taking notes to make sure I was comprehending and not forget the interesting bits. I’d conveniently have all the things I found noteworthy on a sheet/sheets of paper to review at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked well enough, to the point that I started feeling that nonfiction books were superior to fiction because they were more easily embedded – when you finish a fictional novel/series, it is done, complete. But after finishing a nonfiction book, it was not uncommon to find it referenced in another book, or find that its ideas would concretely affect how you thought about things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, it is a few years after college and I am having fun learning things that I find interesting, in a different country, and getting paid for it. Then I notice a strange coincidence: my young adult life so far looks like a modern-day parallel of a typical fantasy/adventure story – a young person backpacks far and wide, sometimes with friends along the way (in this very modern story, I can take my close friends with me because we hang out virtually), and finds the wizard to apprentice themself to, learns magic, traveling far, traveling light. And when things seem uncertain and intimidating, I think of how challenges are essential in making a story interesting. “Things will be okay in the end. If it’s not okay, it’s not the end.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepping back, it is rather tickling to realize there is the potential framing of this as an underdog story, where the humble, frivolous story has a higher level impact on the seemingly more virtuous/practical fact-based/objective nonfiction books. It dictates the story, the overall arc, of your life. I suppose a similar effect may be achieved with biographies. But for some reason I’ve only started reading them more recently. (Also real life role models, but I didn’t have any). But I think the critical bit is that it’s hard to grow in a cohesive direction unless you aspire to a platonic ideal of yourself – but you first need to develop a platonic ideal of yourself (I took this phrase from a twitter post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if that’s related to the problem that’s pervasive among the kids today. I’d think that ordinarily, it’s only critical to do an exploration of narratives/lifestyles if you’re going to deviate from the norm. But now, the default paths have dried up, and many have not explored a wide enough range of narratives to cultivate a deep taste in who they want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I wonder if this relates to depressive nihilism, where my speculated preventative against depressive nihilism is being aware of the things that matter to you. Because even if you think objectively that nothing matters in the end, you feel that things matter to you. And I suspect that’s real enough to live a life out on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;comments solicited, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ajt3UAd71kClzQVXHCj59ue87yCOB8dSimUMIJU3Jdw/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;kludgey comment-able form here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In high school I transitioned from reading a lot of fantasy/adventure to reading nonfiction, like “The Selfish Gene”, “Mutants”, “The Checklist Manifesto”, etc. I remember it was hard – it turned out that I had unconsciously developed the habit of skim-reading, because fantasy/adventure novels tend to have a lot of descriptions that can evoke mental imagery without careful reading. This did not work for the nonfiction I read. I’d go through the motions of reading several pages and not absorb anything I read. I slowly unlearned this habit by keeping a piece of computer paper folded up into quarters as a bookmark, and taking notes to make sure I was comprehending and not forget the interesting bits. I’d conveniently have all the things I found noteworthy on a sheet/sheets of paper to review at the end.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">recommended norms for high quality discussions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/water" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="recommended norms for high quality discussions" /><published>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/shared-norms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/water">&lt;p&gt;I used to be envious of people who were best friends, and now I am lucky to find myself a third of a complementary trio of close friends. It’s been interesting to try to analyze our unspoken norms, our deep assumptions on how you’re supposed to interact with others, which has evidently yet unconsciously facilitated our friendship. Our friendship can be characterized by being highly conversation-intensive, which I highly enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some characteristics we’ve identified, derived from informative cultural clashes with guests. It is derived from a collaborative draft, but I’m taking this as an exercise in editing it in the way I’d better understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identified norms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;separation of personal and factual&lt;/strong&gt;
Taste and logic are extremely distinct, and they both always matter. It’s assumed that all logic is motivated by emotion. There are no objective value judgments. Conversely, there’s always a logic to emotion. Everything outside of the driving emotional core can be challenged, including beliefs about the emotional core. But the fact that there is a core is a given, and it can never be wrong, because feelings are just feelings. We try very hard to distinguish statements of facts and statements of feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;separation of personal and societal&lt;/strong&gt;
We see society’s aesthetic as pretty arbitrary, so we don’t evaluate people’s worth in a broader societal-values sense and tend to come off as nonjudgmental. But we judge things as far as they relate to our interests/tastes; we find people uninteresting or aesthetically displeasing. Apparently, the norm is to put a lot of weight into your own and others’ societal worth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;moral truth seeking vs self-interested purity&lt;/strong&gt;
There is no responsibility to always look for more truth, because there’s so much of it, and also truth is instrumental so you should do what’s interesting to you. In other words, you are permitted to not care about lots of things and put model-flaws on the backburner, as long it is acknowledged as such. The expectation is in trying to purify/make consistent what you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; model and care about. This is distinct from the rationalist norm, where there is moral responsibility to seek the truth immediately; here, truth-seeking is merely because you care.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;good faith&lt;/strong&gt;
Everybody has coherent models and is trying to communicate clearly about them, so even if you disagree, assume that they have something else coherent in view. It’s assumed that mutual understanding is a long, slow process. The conversation is largely about clarifying all the facts so that a convergent understanding arises relatively trivially. At the object level, everything can be questioned, including somebody’s logic and standing. This is sustainable because at the meta level, we always trust each other to be able to align, and that’s why we’re here; it’s never in question as long as we’re present.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;intention orientation&lt;/strong&gt;
It is hard to control emotion, so we tend to read intention much more heavily. This means that harsh tones are often taken impersonally and ignored, unless someone explicitly wants to put it on the table as a factor to consider. This allows the discussion to default towards attempting to build a coherent explanatory model, unless they explicitly want to switch modes towards having emotions assauged. The more prevalent norm seems to expect people to express their emotion right, so that interpreted emotion is assumed to be reality.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;commitment&lt;/strong&gt;
We think it’s important to strive for global coherency in yourself and present yourself to other people with as much consistency as possible. You are expected to be the best judge of your values and have the best vantage point for considering the full trajectory of a decision (see 4. good faith). Therefore we are very accepting of others’ autonomy in decision-making, even if not well-understood. However, the decision maker is always responsible for the outcome. No resentment allowed. It seems more normal to share responsibility in decision-making i.e. resent someone for their influence on your decision.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there deeper trends behind these observations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if these norms arise and converge due to the experience of having a more distant starting point relative to other people, so we are used to assuming a more naive and tolerant stance, combined with a desire to build and improve aesthetic internal frameworks with others. This prioritizes norms that make communication clearer and lower-stakes, especially of otherwise sensitive/taboo internal data and perceptions. In other words, this optimization gives us sufficient degrees of freedom to resolve seeming paradoxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is rather tentative modeling; I am curious how the relatability (or not) to this description corresponds to real life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;comments solicited, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1jF0s0IVLF338Uvgy1RKo4P8roP7ESnwwJGbsBUhwcGQ/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;kludgey comment-able form here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I used to be envious of people who were best friends, and now I am lucky to find myself a third of a complementary trio of close friends. It’s been interesting to try to analyze our unspoken norms, our deep assumptions on how you’re supposed to interact with others, which has evidently yet unconsciously facilitated our friendship. Our friendship can be characterized by being highly conversation-intensive, which I highly enjoy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">on starting to write</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/starting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on starting to write" /><published>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/writing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/starting">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[written 2021/03/23]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading David Lipsky’s “Although of course you end up becoming yourself: A road trip with David Foster Wallace”. It’s not something I would ordinarily pick up, but I’ve been primed because a number of people in my social circles have been talking about David Foster Wallace lately (n=2…but they don’t know each other!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to learn of this book’s existence from a twitter thread that I can no longer find. It quoted this bit by DFW: “…I think that the ultimate way you and I get lucky is if you have some success early in life, you get to find out early it doesn’t mean anything. Which means you get to start early the work of figuring out what does mean something.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very much not a paragon of success, but my mind still goes ‘I know what he’s talking about’. And the interpretation is something like, ‘it doesn’t mean much if others are impressed if you aren’t; it doesn’t matter if others think it means something if you don’t’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s related to undeserved success: I found that it’s one thing to know about it, and it’s another thing to experience it close up. If you’re reminded of imposter syndrome, I agree—it’s like an inverse of imposter syndrome: Though it’s not me whose level of competence is in question (conveniently, I’m too inept to fake anything), but society’s—specifically, their ability to evaluate. It’s led to generalized apathy towards external success markers—they’re proxy measures that I now regard with more suspicion/wariness. It’s a rather unnerving development because it comes with a sense of alienation and detachment from mainstream social narrative-reality of what matters—it seems like a step towards delusion (maybe let me expound on the relatability of a cancer cell in a later post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s an unspoken peril of figuring out what &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; mean something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/think.html&quot;&gt;a nice essay about independent thinking&lt;/a&gt;, but it was about successful independent thought, and I’ve been worrying about unsuccessful independent thought. I’m afraid of becoming a conspiracy theorist. Or delusional — I’ve more recently finished “Logicomix: An Epic Search for Truth”, and they don’t shy away from the association of schizophrenia/delusional thinking and people who are striving to figure things out. I’m definitely not as passionate and meticulous as these logicians, but it is relatable enough to unsettle me. I don’t think you don’t need to be a genius to find ‘A Beautiful Mind’ horrifying. And on my backlog of books to read is “Lost in Math: How Beauty Leads Physics Astray”, because I’ve been saliently using aesthetic/intuition/beauty as a means to choose my mental structures (see: future post on mental interior design).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what to do about this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a preventative practice to this is getting regular feedback. I’ve been extremely fortunate to have friends that help me build and refine mental frameworks. But I’m aware that we’re a specific type of people and few—I’m missing a broader perspective. And so, an obvious solution seems to be to write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a myriad of reasons of why I’m not much of a writer, one reason being that I’m shy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though, not DFW-shy: “I think being shy basically means being self-absorbed to the extent that it makes it difficult to be around other people. For instance, if I’m hanging out with you, I can’t even tell whether I like you or not, because I’m too worried about whether you like me. It’s stressful and unpleasant or whatever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wondered if I was misunderstanding him, but he followed up with,  “Part of the shyness for me is, it’s very easy for me to play this game of, What do you want? What will the effect of this be on you? You know? It’s this kind of mental chess. Which in personal intercourse? Makes things very difficult. But in writing, when I think a lot of what you’re doing—there are very few innocent sentences in writing. You’ve gotta know not just how it looks and sounds to you. But you’ve gotta be able plausibly to project what an alien consciousness will make of it” (24). I definitely don’t do that on a regular basis, so I’m not DFW-shy. In fact my shyness is due to my inability to model others – it’s less worrying about whether they like me, and moreso having minimal perceived feedback, so it’s like writing into a void and not being sure if I’m even understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another excuse is that writing is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even texting is hard—I’m baffled and in awe of people who can text throughout the day on a daily basis. Not that long ago, I learned that some people primarily think in language, so to communicate, it’s pretty straightforward to transcribe their thoughts into speech. I seem to think more in ‘pre-language’; communication is more like trying to describe a scenery or cloud of concepts. I often get tripped up in knowing where to start, and in linearizing ideas that don’t have a linear structure. I’m not sure if it’s a legitimate excuse, but I wonder if this contributes to ease-of-communication baselines. The hope is that I’ll develop better transcription heuristics as I write more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I’m starting to write now because while these frictions haven’t decreased, the incentives have increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As DFW also astutely notes, “somebody who’s writing, has part of their motivation to sort of I think impress themselves and their consciousness on others. There’s an unbelievable arrogance about even trying to write something…” And, well, I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; trying to asserting/indulging my sense of aesthetic here. Arrogantly, maybe tautologically, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/eat/&quot;&gt;I do like my aesthetic&lt;/a&gt;. But part of my taste is in the integrity of the ideas, and I’ve been feeling the limitations of my current approach for a while now. The ideas in my head don’t feel sufficiently processed and &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/poop/forgetfully.html&quot;&gt;compressed&lt;/a&gt;, and all advice seems to point to writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I anticipate these writing exercises to mainly benefit myself, there’s some small hope that it could be a source of solidarity. I’ve recently finished a book called “Discovering: Inventing and Solving Problems at the Frontiers of Scientific Knowledge” (Root-Bernstein), and on the last page, it said, “If what we’ve said and done here gives such a person the courage to do science on his own and in his own way–you know I mean her, too–then we have succeeded in producing something important” (428). Unlike other independently-thinking people I know, I’m often much more uncertain and unconfident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason I picked up the book “Although of course you end up becoming yourself” was because I like the title. It reads like a reassurance—&lt;em&gt;you’ll find your way, eventually&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;comments solicited, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1qpSEuLDHJtHC38dWwjdwWorMSu0OhHnOf1xdrBf7T3Q/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;kludgey comment-able form here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">[written 2021/03/23]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to ask good questions?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/good_questions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to ask good questions?" /><published>2023-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/good-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/good_questions">&lt;p&gt;A friend recently introduced me to “the paradox of inquiry”, specifically the idea that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anamnesis_(philosophy)&quot;&gt;‘questions came from knowledge that your soul had but forgot and is trying to remember’&lt;/a&gt;. So maybe I have a lot of questions because I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;dll110.github.io/poop/forgetfully&quot;&gt;forgotten&lt;/a&gt; so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow it’s hard to notice if you ask more questions than average, but it’s been mentioned often enough over the years that I’m presuming there’s a trend somewhere. Curiously, it does not really help me write good prompts to chatgpt, given the lackluster answers it gives me. I am decent at googling though, so it’s probably learnt (I’m not really sure why I’m not compelled to learn LLM prompting though).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to ask questions when something is interesting because it lights up a lot of potential paths in your brain. This seems to be what Plato/Socrates observed, where it’s easier to ask questions when you already know about a topic. I think it’s because these tend to be questions to help &lt;em&gt;refine&lt;/em&gt; the shape of an area, and the degree of resolution is such that your questions can be relatively pointed and specific. Questions that people consider ‘good’ seem to more of this type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s harder to ask questions in a void, because without some basic knowledge, there’s no expectations. And with no expectations, there’s no surprise; with no surprise, there’s no questions, at least of a clarifying type. But then you can turn to orienting questions, questions for obtaining a mass of content that you can later shape and refine. I find myself feeling more clunky in this realm, but I wonder if it’s somewhat the nature of these types of questions: they naturally have less hooks, and so come less reflexively and tend to be rather generic. Perhaps they get the perception of being dumb questions because they don’t show off any existing understanding. I think they’re especially important though and I need to intentionally work to improve upon these for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve adopted the notion that a bad question is better than no question. This is mostly a tool for overcoming self-consciousness, which is not really important, especially relative to the opportunity to understand something better (in general, I have not yet identified an area where it is better to give heavy consideration towards your pride). And if it is an effort towards that, it is a worthy question, even if it is to help you understand how to ask better questions (though I should probably caveat that I haven’t historically been pestered by questions, partially because I prefer to be on the question-asking side of things).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are at least three artificial categories for asking questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exploring an unknown/new field – how to get content/mass to shape things; what objects are there? getting the other to be more verbose is generally better here. ‘why’, ‘tell me more’ are examples here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;feeling out the shape of an area/concept; figuring out what it is and what it is not; trying on various metaphors/parallels to see how well they fit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a miscellaneous category, because it’s artificial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do notice that I seem to have a lot of question relative to answers, so here are some representative standing questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would it take to automate question-asking? How would you automate it? Some complex method would be to give it motivation/ideals/target, mostly because I find it much harder to ask questions when I am not interested. What drives the feeling of being interested?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is asking good questions generally easier in a 1:1 setting versus in a group setting? Versus asking a chatbot? Maybe something about the correlation with a tighter feedback loop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
 
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;questions and answers solicited, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ucoRxBOt1kkWkw0vaB1TYxA93SZ9yT2aTwouTgffBPk/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;kludgey comment-able form here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A friend recently introduced me to “the paradox of inquiry”, specifically the idea that ‘questions came from knowledge that your soul had but forgot and is trying to remember’. So maybe I have a lot of questions because I’ve forgotten so much.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">on being scoopable</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poop/scoop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="on being scoopable" /><published>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poop/scoopable</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poop/scoop">&lt;p&gt;I attended a number of seminars this week, and a number of them self-consciously joked about being scooped. This is not really frequency illusion – I’m pretty sure it’s a cultural norm/meme. I’ve never really understood it though. Wouldn’t it just be validation/consilience that you’re on the right track? And that means you can get your curiosities solved without doing the work! You can turn your attention to the other things you’re interested in.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Take it from someone who’s been scooped, of sorts:
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Around 2019, I went to a talk by Marinka Zitnik and learned about the Stanford SNAP page, where I learned about the TreeOfLife dataset. Later I read Erik Hoel’s emergence paper around the same time, and realized I could apply his measure to the TreeOfLife dataset. Evidence: https://github.com/dll110/treeoflife I never finished it though because it was just a side-hobby (my actual research work had nothing to do with either of these topics directly) and I got distracted by other things.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Then last year I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/ib/article/13/12/283/6474503&quot;&gt;“Evolution and emergence: higher order information structure in protein interactomes across the tree of life”&lt;/a&gt; when looking through Michael Levin’s publications:  Pretty much EI-Net + TreeOfLife data. Published by the original EI peeps and Michael Levin – I’d bet they have sound thinking. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Which means I have proof that I have great ideas. A full two years before they published. My intuitions are validated without me having to write up a full paper. And I wouldn’t have gotten such validation if I had actually written it. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Of course, it would’ve been an actually cool paper to have under my belt, but that’s more of a resume thing than a personal thing. 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In “Letters to a Young Scientist”, E.O. Wilson wrote ‘look for a field that is sparsely inhabited; look for a chance to break away, to find a subject you can make your own…shy away from subjects that are receiving a great deal of attention, if it has a glamorous aura, if its practitioners are prizewinners who receive large grants…take a subject instead that interests you and looks promising, where established experts are not yet competing with each other’. (45)
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The takeaway is, if your poop is getting scooped, find pastures elsewhere. Your poop is better served fertilizing a new field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;


&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I attended a number of seminars this week, and a number of them self-consciously joked about being scooped. This is not really frequency illusion – I’m pretty sure it’s a cultural norm/meme. I’ve never really understood it though. Wouldn’t it just be validation/consilience that you’re on the right track? And that means you can get your curiosities solved without doing the work! You can turn your attention to the other things you’re interested in. Take it from someone who’s been scooped, of sorts: Around 2019, I went to a talk by Marinka Zitnik and learned about the Stanford SNAP page, where I learned about the TreeOfLife dataset. Later I read Erik Hoel’s emergence paper around the same time, and realized I could apply his measure to the TreeOfLife dataset. Evidence: https://github.com/dll110/treeoflife I never finished it though because it was just a side-hobby (my actual research work had nothing to do with either of these topics directly) and I got distracted by other things. Then last year I came across “Evolution and emergence: higher order information structure in protein interactomes across the tree of life” when looking through Michael Levin’s publications: Pretty much EI-Net + TreeOfLife data. Published by the original EI peeps and Michael Levin – I’d bet they have sound thinking. Which means I have proof that I have great ideas. A full two years before they published. My intuitions are validated without me having to write up a full paper. And I wouldn’t have gotten such validation if I had actually written it. Of course, it would’ve been an actually cool paper to have under my belt, but that’s more of a resume thing than a personal thing. In “Letters to a Young Scientist”, E.O. Wilson wrote ‘look for a field that is sparsely inhabited; look for a chance to break away, to find a subject you can make your own…shy away from subjects that are receiving a great deal of attention, if it has a glamorous aura, if its practitioners are prizewinners who receive large grants…take a subject instead that interests you and looks promising, where established experts are not yet competing with each other’. (45) The takeaway is, if your poop is getting scooped, find pastures elsewhere. Your poop is better served fertilizing a new field.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">an ode to video speed controller</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/eat/with_speed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="an ode to video speed controller" /><published>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/eat/with_speed</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/eat/with_speed">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../documents/optimal speed.png&quot; alt=&quot;optimal speed&quot; style=&quot;width:300px;height:400px;float: right;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever not comprehended what someone was saying because they were talking too slow and you forgot the first half of their sentence, you should &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/video-speed-controller/nffaoalbilbmmfgbnbgppjihopabppdk?hl=en&quot;&gt;download video speed controller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been avoiding watching things because the inability to control information/interestingness density (like you can do with reading) is frustrating, you should &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/video-speed-controller/nffaoalbilbmmfgbnbgppjihopabppdk?hl=en&quot;&gt;download video speed controller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re underestimating the ability of your mind to adapt to and normalize speed changes, you should &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/video-speed-controller/nffaoalbilbmmfgbnbgppjihopabppdk?hl=en&quot;&gt;download video speed controller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you watch videos and will die eventually, you should &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/video-speed-controller/nffaoalbilbmmfgbnbgppjihopabppdk?hl=en&quot;&gt;download video speed controller&lt;/a&gt;.
If you think our lack of speed is embarrassing (see Fig. 1), you should &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/video-speed-controller/nffaoalbilbmmfgbnbgppjihopabppdk?hl=en&quot;&gt;download video speed controller&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video speed controller has changed more lives than the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dll110.github.io/eat/&quot;&gt;texts I learned to cut a pdf for&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>